<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An excellent treatise touching the restoring againe of him that is fallen written by the worthy, Saint Chrysostome to Theodorus a friend of his, who by leud liuing, was fallen from the Gospell; fit to read for reclaiming their hearts which are in like case. Englished (out of an auncient Latin translation, written in velume) by R.W. With an annexed epistle of comfort from one friend to another, wherin the Anabaptists error of desperation is briefly confuted, and the sinne against the holy Ghost plainly declared.</title>
            <author>John Chrysostom, Saint, d. 407.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1609</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 187 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 108 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04503</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14631</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S121653</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99856824</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99856824</idno>
            <idno type="VID">22457</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04503)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 22457)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 441:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An excellent treatise touching the restoring againe of him that is fallen written by the worthy, Saint Chrysostome to Theodorus a friend of his, who by leud liuing, was fallen from the Gospell; fit to read for reclaiming their hearts which are in like case. Englished (out of an auncient Latin translation, written in velume) by R.W. With an annexed epistle of comfort from one friend to another, wherin the Anabaptists error of desperation is briefly confuted, and the sinne against the holy Ghost plainly declared.</title>
                  <author>John Chrysostom, Saint, d. 407.</author>
                  <author>Cottesford, Thomas. Epistle of comfort.</author>
                  <author>Wolcomb, Robert, b. 1567 or 8.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 191, [13] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by J. Windet] for I. Helme, and are to be sold at his shop at S. Dunstans Church,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1609]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name, date of publication and author of part two from STC.</note>
                  <note>In two parts. Dedication to part one signed by the translator: Rob. Wolcomb. Part two has a separate dated title page (register and pagination are continuous) that reads: An epistle of comfort. It is signed at end: T.C. (i.e. Thomas Cottesford).</note>
                  <note>The "Epistle" is printed in STC 26140 and STC 5841.5--Cf. STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Repentance --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Anabaptists --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Salvation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:22457:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:22457:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN EXCELLENT Treatiſe touching the reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring againe of him that is fallen;</p>
            <p>Written by the worthy, Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> to <hi>Theodorus</hi> a friend of his, who by leud liuing, was fallen from the Goſpell; fit to read for reclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming their hearts which are in like caſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Engliſhed (out of an auncient Latin tranſlation, written in Velume) by</hi> R.W.</p>
            <p>With an annexed Epiſtle of comfort from one friend to another, where in the Anabaptiſts error of deſperation is briefly confuted, and the ſinne againſt the holy Ghoſt plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly declared.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Heb. 3.13.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Exhort ye one another daily, while it is called to day.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON Printed for <hi>I. Helme,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop at S. Dunſtans Church</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="translators_preface">
                  <pb facs="tcp:22457:2"/>
                  <head>Of the profit of this Treatiſe.</head>
                  <l>THe prince of Surgeons, Phoebus ſonne,</l>
                  <l>In curing famous was:</l>
                  <l>Machaon and his brother too,</l>
                  <l>By art brought much to pas.</l>
                  <l>The beſt of theſe in feſtered ſores</l>
                  <l>Did all, and could no more:</l>
                  <l>To ſoule of man corrupt by ſinne,</l>
                  <l>Their skill denied a dore.</l>
                  <l>But heere behold 'gainſt dreadfull crimes</l>
                  <l>A ſoueraigne medcine lies:</l>
                  <l>A Moly, Panaceia ſweete,</l>
                  <l>To him that vpward ſties.</l>
                  <l>If fallen downe thou feele diſpaire,</l>
                  <l>Read through this pamphlet ſmall:</l>
                  <l>It Theôn cheiras, powerfull ſalue,</l>
                  <l>In ſuch aſſaults maiſt call.</l>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>R. W.</signed>
                  </closer>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.3.</bibl>
                        <p>It is ſufficient for vs that we haue ſpent the time paſt of the life, after the luſt of the Gentiles, walking in wantonneſſe, luſts, drun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>enneſſe, gluttonie, drinkings, and in abominable idolatries.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:22457:2"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>To the Worſhipfull and his ſpecial good friend, Maſter IOHN KEMP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THORNE Eſquier, R.W.</hi> wiſheth in this life proſperous ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe in all affaires, and in the life to come a crowne of glorie.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Eeing alwayes it hath bin ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted a ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous worke, either to commend in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollo</hi> wiſedome, or to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toll in <hi>Hercules</hi> puiſſance, or to prayſe in <hi>Minerua</hi> knowledge: it may bee
<pb facs="tcp:22457:3"/> thought no leſſe needleſſe for mee, to prayſe in fined wordes and garniſhed ſtile (if ſo I were able to doe) your ardent zeale in Gods truth, and maruellous af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection towardes the true profeſſors thereof. And becauſe among thoſe that know you, it ſhineth ſo o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riently, as in words to ſet it foorth, were rather to imbeazle than illuſtrate it; and among thoſe that know you not, by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending it abundantly, may feare the cenſure of ſmoothing, I thinke it better, at this time (as <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lust</hi> ſaith of Carthage) to ſpeake nothing at all of it than a little. Yet ſurely (though the enuious hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily
<pb facs="tcp:22457:3"/> miſlike it) this I af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, when I bethought to finde a meete protector for this pamphlet, that might loue it, as Antoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us the Emperor was wont to loue books, as <hi>Alphon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> was accuſtomed to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme the workes of <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cero,</hi> that might reade it diligently as <hi>Eraſmus</hi> did <hi>Terence,</hi> as Biſhop <hi>Iewell</hi> did <hi>Horace,</hi> as Ladie <hi>Iane Graie</hi> did <hi>Platoes Phae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don:</hi> none came to my minde before your Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, vnder the wings of whoſe tuition, theſe my ſlender labors might ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be ſhadowed, from all the malice of ſpitefull re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proouers and taunting
<pb facs="tcp:22457:4"/> carpers. Now concerning the worke, ſome I knowe will finde fault with my preſumption, that being a tender ſuckling and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice in good letters, I would dare to put foorth ought in print, eſpecially in ſuch a plentifull time of bookes. Let theſe take this aunſwere; that I did it not voluntarily but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced, and that by the requeſt, not of one or two, but of many, whoſe good will I haue often experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, whoſe friendſhip in the Lorde I will not (for a ſmall cauſe) violate, whoſe authoritie I may not deſpiſe. For lighting by chaunce on this treatiſe
<pb facs="tcp:22457:4"/> of <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> reueren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing it at the firſt ſight more for antiquitie than ought elſe, aſſoone as I had read it ouer, I did it faithfully for my priuate vtilitie into Engliſh, neuer thinking it ſhould come to this paſſe. But hauing lent it vnto ſome of my friends, deſirous of ſuch a peece of matter, they fell ſuddenly into that liking and louing of it, that they neuer ceaſed exhorting, begging, compelling (I may ſay) vntill (maugre my head) I graunted, it ſhould goe foorth for the benefit of many. Which now beeing newly borne and come into the world,
<pb facs="tcp:22457:5"/> I beſeech your courteſie to receiue into your pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage: and as it procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from a willing minde, ſo to take it with a glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome countenance. And notwithſtanding this te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie of a gratefull minde, doe not any way counterpoiſe the weight of your demerits, yet I beſeech you to accept of the poore widowes mites. and of the cheerefull gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers minde. Thus ſurcea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing any longer to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt your Worſhips ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous affaires, I ſuppliantly craue of the Almightie, dayly to augment his gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in you and the vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Gentlewoman your
<pb facs="tcp:22457:5"/> wife, that after your race run in this dale of miſerie, you may for euer enioy the ſight of Chriſt Ieſus in heauen.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your worſhips daily and humble Orator, <hi>ROB. WOLCOMB.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="treatise">
                  <pb facs="tcp:22457:6"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22457:6"/>
                  <head>Of the reſtoring againe of him that is fallen.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>H;<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iere.</hi> 9.1.</note> that my head were (full) of water and mine eies a fountaine of teares Much more fitly it is ſpoken of mee now,<note place="margin">The wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thines &amp; integritie once of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to whom he writeth. <hi>Ecclu.</hi> 16.3</note> then at that time of the Prophet of God. For how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit not many cities, neither a whole countrey is to bee la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented of me, yet I muſt mourne for a ſoule of more worth than many nations, of more price than many cities. For if one that doe the will of God, be better than a great companie of the wicked thou alſo waſt better once, than ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:22457:7"/> multitudes of the Iewes. Wherefore let no man won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, if I peraduenture vſe more large lamentations at this time,<note place="margin">The cauſe of the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> and powre out were plenty of teares, than at that time the Prophet did (For as I ſaid) I do not bewaile y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of a city which is taken, nor the thraldome of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon people little ſet by: but the downfall of an excellent ſoule, and the ruine of a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple which Chriſt inhabited. If any euer knew the orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of thy mind, which now the flame of the diuel hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed; if any euer beheld the temple of thy body, when it glittered with the brightneſſe of chaſtitie; ſoothly he would deeme that lamentation of the Prophet ſmall and much inferior: wherein hee bewai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth that the handes of Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barians had prophaned the holy place, and that the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies fire had deſtroied the Temple, &amp; that the Cherubin
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:22457:7"/> and the Arke were defiled, and that the mercy ſeat, with the tables of ſtone, and the golden potte, were polluted. For this lamentation which I vſe, is by ſo much more piteous and bitter than the other; by how much more truly and euident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly all theſe things were to bee ſeene in thy ſoule, than be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the wals of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; the Temple which was in thee, was much holier than the other. It ſhined not with the mettals of golde and ſiluer but with the vertues of the mind, and giftes of the holy Ghoſt: it had within it the Arke and the two Cherubins, that is, the faith of the father, and the ſonne, and the holy Ghoſt.<note place="margin">The wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched plight wherein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this man was fallen.</note> Yet now nought of all theſe is left, all things are taken from thy ſoule, ſhe is bereft of all her beautie, and all the giftes which God beſtowed on her, ſhe remaineth ſpoiled, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, fowle, ſhe hath loſt all her aide and ſafegard.</p>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:22457:8"/>
                  <p>No doore now is ſhut in her, no entrie is kept, but ſhe lyeth open to all naughtie ſpirits, which corrupt the ſoule. No vncleane thought, no filthie deſire is thence expelled but if the ſpirit of fornication come, it entreth in, if the ſpirit of pride, if the ſpirit of auarice, if more helliſh and vnpure, than theſe ſhall come none forbiddeth them, none bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth them backe. For ſhe hath no keeper, no Sexton. And as to the ſecrets of heauen there is no acceſſe for an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly perſon; ſo at the firſt no infection could touch thy mind.</p>
                  <p>But perhaps I may ſeeme to ſpeake incredible things, to thoſe eſpecially that knew not thy former eſtate, and onely ſee the deſtruction wherein thy ſoule now lieth. This ſurely is the cauſe why I weepe without remedie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I knew thee: and why I ſorrow vnceſſantly, becauſe
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:22457:8"/> I remember how long it is, vntill I ſee thee returne vnto thy wonted and priſtine glory. Which for all that men may iudge impoſſible.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.26</note> 
                     <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 113.8, 9. 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.8</note> For he it is, that raiſeth the needy out or the duſt, &amp; lifteth vp the poore out of the dunge. That he may ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t him with princes (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uen) with the princes of the people He it is that maketh the bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren woman to dwell with a family, and a ioyfull mother of children.</p>
                  <p>Let vs not then doubt nor deſpaire,<note place="margin">If Sathan draw to ſin, God can pull backe to goodnes.</note> but that thou may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt be conuerted into a better caſe. For if the diuell could do ſo much in thee, as to draw thee from the height of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue to the depth of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, how much more ſhal God be able to reclaime thee to the higheſt pitch of goodneſſe, and not onely make thee that thou waſt once, but farre more bleſſed than thou diddeſt ſeeme in thy owne conceit. Onely be of ſtout courage, neither
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:22457:9"/> caſt of the hope of goodneſſe: let not, I pray thee, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tide thee, which doth the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe.<note place="margin">Vngodli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tencie breedeth to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire.</note> It is impietie not the multitude of ſinnes, that brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth a foole to deſperation: and therefore <hi>Salomon</hi> ſayd not, that each one when hee commeth into the depth of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils contemneth, but,<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Pro.</hi> 18.3</note> the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked (ſaith he) if he come into the depth of euils contemneth. It is then a point of the impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to haue no hope of ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,<note place="margin">Or, when the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> commeth contempt.</note> and to contemne when they come into the depth of ſinnes, vngodlineſſe not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting them to haue reſpect to God, and to returne thither from whence they fell So that this thought which cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth away all hope of conuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, iſſueth from impietie, and as a moſt heauie ſtone accloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſoule, it perpetually compelleth it to behold the earth and neuer to looke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward on God.<note place="margin">When we ſinne we muſt not deſpaire.</note> But a luſty ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke and loftie minde will
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:22457:9"/> caſt down this hurtful weight of his ſoule, and tread vnder feet Sathan, that being his owne gouernour hee may ſing the Pſalmiſts words of God,<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 113 2.</note> As the eies of ſeruans looke vpon the hands of their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and as the eies of a mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den vpon the hands of her mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtres, ſo our eyes waite vpon the Lord our God, till he haue mercy vpon vs. Haue mercy vpon vs, O Lord haue mercy vpon vs, for we haue ſuffered too much contempt. And in theſe wordes of this heauenly prophecie, there is ſingular doctrine, we haue ſuffered too much contempt. This is that hee would haue vs ſay, that although for the multitude of our ſinnes wee haue ſuffered much contempt, and are ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rounded with reproches, yet our eyes ſhall waite vpon the Lord our God till hee haue mercy vpon vs, &amp; that we will not leaue of beſeeching vntill we be vouchſafed forgiuenes.</p>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:22457:10"/>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">We ought to be ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt in prayer when wee ſue for forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and not to reſt till God haue ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled our petitions.</note>For this is the badge of a conſtant and ſetled minde that it is not wearie of perſeuering in intrearie through diſpaire to obtaine, but continueth and perſiſteth in crauing, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the Lord haue mercy vpon it.<note n="*" place="margin">Theſe two peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ods fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing G.F. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pito hath not in his tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> And leaſt you ſhould think you offende greatly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord, if not vouchſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed to be heard, you continue importunately in prayers, call to memory the Euangelicall parable, and there you ſhall find, that the Lord ſheweth, that ſtiffe &amp; perſeuering beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers are not vnacceptable to him. For he ſaith,<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Lu.</hi> 11.8.</note> Though he would not giue him becauſe he is his friend, yet becauſe of his importunitie. he will riſe and giue him as much as hee needeth. Vnderſtand therefore (deare friend) that the diuell putteth into our mindes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire of obteining, to this end, that he may cut from vs the hope of the goodneſſe of God, which is the Anchor of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:22457:10"/> our ſaluation, the foundation <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f life, the guide of the way <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hrough which wee paſſe to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eauen: in briefe, the Apoſtle <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aith.<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Ro.</hi> 8.24.</note> by hope we are ſaued. Inſomuch that our ſaluation conſiſteth in hope, which draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th vp our ſoules from out the earth, knit (as it were) to certaine chaines hanging downe from heauen, and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth againe thoſe to the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly dwelling place which cleaue to themſelues, exalting them ſecurely aboue the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of this life, and earthly miſeries. Wherefore if any en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbred with theſe calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, bee diſſolute, and let goe out of his hands the anchor of hope, hee muſt needes fall, and be caried into the bottom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe pit and profunditie of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils.<note place="margin">The dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of deſpaire</note> Which aſſoone as the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie ſhall perceiue, and ſee vs loath the multitude of our ſinnes, and feare through re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morſe of conſcience, ſtraight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way he draweth neere, and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:22457:11"/> before our eyes cogitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of deſpaire, more heauie than any leade or grauell which if wee vndertake, we muſt of neceſſity bee drowned in the depth or euils, becauſe, with the very load, the ſtaies of our ſaluation are broken. Into the which depth becauſe thou art caſt, thou doſt throw behind thee the precepts of a good and gentle lord, and thou doeſt obey the becke of a blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and mercileſſe tyrant,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.30.</note> the enemie of thy ſaluation. Thou haſt ſhaken off the ſweete yoke of Chriſt, and haſt laid on thy necke for it, the hard and iron fetters of ſinne: thou haſt ſhaken off the eaſie bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of a lowly and meeke Lord, and for it haſt hanged about thy neck a milſtone, but how long doeſt thou ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue? Stand now at the laſt, and ceaſe to drown thy vnhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py ſoule, without any care, without any aduiſe how long doeſt thou haſt it foorth, and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:22457:11"/> caſt it downe headlong to thy owne decay?<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luke</hi> 15.</note> And truly the woman in the Goſpell, which found againe the loſt groate, called together her friends and neighbours, that they ſhould reioyce with her: but I will cal youre &amp; my friends &amp; neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours together, and will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat them to meet, not that they ſhould be glad, but that they ſhould lament with mee: not that they ſhould reioyce, but mourne with me, &amp; great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſorrow, lifting vp their hands to heauen, as they ſhall ſee me to doe, and I will ſay vnto them; howle and lament with me, O my friends, pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er out and bring foorth with me fountaines and floods of teares, not for that I haue loſt vnporzable weights of golde, or innumerable ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents of ſiluer; not becauſe I haue loſt threades full of coſtlie pearles, but for that my friend<note n="*" place="margin">Amicus alter i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſe.</note> dearer than any gold, and more pretious than any
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:22457:12"/> ſtone, is (I knowe not how) while he ſailed with vs ouer the large and broad ſea of this life, fallen downe into the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry depth of deſtruction. And if ſome one of my friends ſhall goe about to comfort, and will me to leane of ſorrowing I will aunſwere him in the Prophets words:<note n="*" place="margin">Or, let me alone, I wil weep bitterly, you can not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort me.</note> Suffer me to we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pe moſt bitterly, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hold on comforting mee: for I weepe n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t through the affection of the fleſh, neither is my lamentation woman like, wherein appeare immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate teares to be blamed. I mourne for that, which th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> great and famous Apoſtle S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith hee mourneth for when as he ſaith:<note n="*" place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.22.</note> That I may mourne for them that haue ſinned, and haue not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The death of the ſoule is pitifully to be lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the death of the body is ſo bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken.</note>Certes with reaſon ſhall one rebuke thoſe that for the common death of their friends weepe without meane; but when the wounds not of a bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:22457:12"/> but of a ſoule are lamented, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd of ſuch a ſoule, which in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eath it ſelfe ſheweth ſignes of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er former beautie, and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erous gaineſſe, &amp; with liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> tokens diſplaieth the floure <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f vertues extinguiſhed in her, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ho is ſo cruell, &amp; vnacquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed with vertue, that would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ot be prouoked to teares? For it is a point in Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hie, to forbeare weeping for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ommon death: ſo in the death <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f a ſoule, and ſuch a ſoule <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o receiue comfort. I adiudge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oth vngodly and irreligious. For ordinary death to keepe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he eyes from teares, is the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hiefeſt thinge in the ſtudie of wiſedome: but how ſhall not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e ſeeme to be lamented for without intermiſſion, who of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ate reckned the whole braue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the bodie, but like <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>arued ſtones, who accounted gold as clay, who reſpected all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>elights as durt, and now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ttached by the ſodaine feuers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f luſt and voluptie, being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:22457:13"/> of the integrity an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> beautie of his mind, hath ſha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken hands with vertue, and i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> become a ſlane to vice an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> pleaſure? This man ſhall I not bewaile? This man ſhal I not moyſten ſo long with riuer of teares, vntill wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> weeping I ſtirre vp feeling i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> him, and by the warmth o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> teares I raiſe ſome liuely mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tions in him, if mournin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> may doe ought? And i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> mourners of the body ceaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> not from lamenting, though they aſſuredly know, thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> weeping profite them nothing to renew the life of him tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> is dead: why ſhould not we that know the ſoule may be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> called from death by conuerſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on, earneſtly follow after the medicine of repentance, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> (euen the ſepulchre being ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned) with abundance of teares hee may bee recouered? Yea alſo I thinke we are to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed of ſluggardie, ſith the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menters of bodies and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:22457:13"/> death doe weepe ſo much &amp; continually (yet certaine as we ſaid, that they ſhal not raiſe againe their dead,) if we that know, that by repentance (la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation coupled w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> it) a ſoule may be reſtored to his former eſtate (for the kingly Prophet ſaid.<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 65. Or, in the graue who ſhall praiſe thee.</note> In hell who ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe thy name?) do nothing ſo.</p>
                  <p>We know too, that diuers in the dayes both of vs and our anceſtors hauing ſliden out of the ſtraight path, and ſtraied from the entrance of the narrow way, were ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine reſtored, that their end anſwered their beginning, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the goale and crowne, yea they were thought to haue place among the number of the Saints. But as long as one remaineth in the flame &amp; for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace of luſt, theſe things ſeeme inpoſſible to him although<note n="*" place="margin">A thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand.</note> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finit examples ſhuld be alleged. But if ſome ſmall conuerſion be begun, and the penitent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon caſt vpward his eyes that
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:22457:14"/> burning flame will tarry be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind him, and by how much more ſwiftly he ſhall take his pace, by ſo much more, before him ſhall hee ſee all thinges ſumpled with the coale of an heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly dew.<note place="margin">Deſpaire the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to our ſaluation.</note> So much worth is it that wee beware of one thing, the greateſt enemy to our ſaluation, to our conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, to our repentance, to wit deſperation: which if it take hold in our mind, how great deſire ſoeuer we haue of ſaluation, how great purpoſe ſoeuer to liue euerlaſtingly, if (I ſay) deſpaire come, all the entry to ſaluation is ſtopped, the way to repentance is hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, and the beginning of anguiſh is engendred. And how then ſhall he, that is out of the way, and to whom the doore is ſhut, ve able to doe any good worke, when as (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe deſpaire prohibiteth) he cannot come to the entrance of goodnes? For this cauſe the Diuell goeth about with
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:22457:14"/> tooth and naile, to plant in our hearts ſuch manner of cogita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. For if the feare of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire ſhall remooue vs from the way of vertue, he hath no long combate with vs, for why ſhould hee aſſault when none reſiſteth? And whoſo ſhall haue the power to vndoe this knot, incontinent his ſtrength returneth, the luſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his mind encreaſeth, he ſhall be delighted with the renuing of thoſe contentions: the reaſon is, he ſhall ſee him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe chaſe the chaſer, and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue the perſecuter. And if in caſe (as in wraſtling it falleth out) he faulter againe and fall, let him not be out of hope for ſhame, but remember, that is not the law of wreſtling and iuſting, not once to fall (for he may not be ſaid to be conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that falleth) but in the end not to yeeld, for hee that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire hath mayſtered, how can he either recouer might in contention, or withſtand and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:22457:15"/> fight, ſeeing hee taketh his heeles, and doth not at all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to the conflict? Neither thinke that I ſpeake of thoſe alonely, that haue trangreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in ſmall and not much important things, but my ſpeech is of him that hath made himſelfe a villaine to all miſchiefe, and hath dammed to himſelfe the way to the kingdome of heauen, and was one of the number not of the incredulous miſcreants, but of them that liked God, and after this hath either fallen into fornication, or into all ſortes of vnchaſtitie, which (as the Apoſtle ſaith)<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Ephe.</hi> 5.3.</note> to name is vnſeemely. This man (I ſay) ought not to miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubt of ſaluation, though ſuch wickedneſſe enuiron him euen to the laſt gaſpe.<note place="margin">The an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of God is not paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and therefore though we ſinne, yet his wrath may bee changed into mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie.</note> But harken what the cauſe of this is. If the wrath of God were an affection that did worke a paſſion, we might rightly ſay, that the flame of it kindled
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:22457:15"/> with ſo many and ſuch euils, might not be quenched: but for as much as the truth teacheth that the nature of God is void of paſſions we muſt learn that though God puniſh, though he plague, he doth it not with a wrathfull paſſion, but with vnſpeakeable gentleneſſe, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about to cure vs, not to confound vs, and therefore with gladneſſe will receiue the penitent. For the plaiſter of repentance (if thou ſeeke it) healeth the ſoule, and defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth thee from the anger of God, which he conceiued for thine offences. God doth not (as I ſaid) puniſh a ſinner for his owne fantaſie,<note place="margin">Why God puniſheth man.</note> when he reuengeth his wrong (for the nature of God is not capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of ſuch an affection) but for our profite; he doth all things for our vtilitie, and he chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth and correcteth not to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge himſelfe, but to amend vs.</p>
                  <p>And if any perſiſt in hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:22457:16"/> as the man that turneth his eyes from the light, dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth nothing the light, but damneth himſelfe to darkenes; ſo he that contemneth vertue through a heart that cannot repent, eſtrangeth himſelfe from ſaluation. And as a Phyſition that ſuffreth wrong at the handes of phrenticke and braineſicke men, ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not, nor is diſpleaſed a whit at it, but doth all things that appertaine to eaſe the maladie of the patient, (for the wrong is cauſed by paine:) &amp; as you may ſee the Phyſition glad at a little amendment of the ſicke perſon, and to execute the reſidue of his charge with ioy and cheerefulnes, not kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping in mind the wrong done, but reſpecting the health of the patient: ſo, much rather God,<note place="margin">God is willing to haue vs returne.</note> when wee are become ſtarke wood, is not greedy of vengeance for our treſpaſſes, but deſirous to heale our olde and putrified biles; for to this
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:22457:16"/> end he ſaith &amp; doth all things, thirſting after our ſafetie, not our puniſhment.</p>
                  <p>And albeit reaſon ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently ſhew the contrary, yet leaſt you ſhould ſtagger in the matter, we are able to auouch it out of the holy Scriptures. Tell me what more wicked body was there euer then the king of Babylon? Who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing found out in many things the omnipotency of God,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.46.</note> in ſo much that hee worſhipped his Prophet, and commaunded Frankencenſe and Myrrhe to be offered to him:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.</note> yet againe in deſpight of God he retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to his wonted hawtineſſe, and did caſt ioyntly into the ouen of burning fire, thoſe that refuſed to worſhip his image, becauſe they preferred the ſeruice of God. Neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe, God allured to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and gaue occaſion of recanting to this ſo bloody, and wicked a king. Firſt in this,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.</note> that with the three chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:22457:17"/> he appeared vnto him in the ouen; afterward in that he cauſed him to ſee the viſion which <hi>Daniel</hi> interpreted,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Dan.</hi> 4.</note> that was able to mollifie euen an heart of flint. But when hee was warned by workes, the Prophet alſo exhorted him by wordes, and he receiued the counſell of the Prophet, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Dan.</hi> 4.</note> Wherefore, O king, let my counſell be ecceptabe vnto thee, and breake off thy ſinnes by righteouſnes, and thine ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities by mercy towards the poore for, let there be an hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of thine errour.</p>
                  <p>What ſateſt then to this, O thou wiſe and bleſſed man? Yet is there a returning after ſo great ſlides? credite mee there is, after grieuous ſicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and from the doore of death proceedeth health, and after deſperate ſins many waxe wiſe. For loe (as we ſhewed afore) this king of Babel had now ſtapped all way of ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in that hee prouoked the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:22457:17"/> Lord to wrath, who made him, and exalted him to the throne of a kingdom, who reuealed al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to him heauenly myſteries who imparted on him the know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge of things to come, &amp; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſed to him the ſecrets of all his kingdom, who confounded by the diuine ſolution of his prophet, the iuglings of the wiſe men, Aſtrologers, Gaza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rens, &amp; Caldeans, &amp; opened to the capacity of a child, by a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine interpretatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a hidden ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret: inſomuch that he ſeemed not only to beleeue in the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt God, but to proclaime tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughout al the world, that the God of <hi>Daniel</hi> was the true God; yet after this he fell into ſuch an outrage, that he threw headlong into the hot burning ouen the ſeruants of God that would not worſhis his image. And yet ne here doth the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of God forget to cure &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy him, but in the midſt of the fire, when he had put to the flame, the children that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:22457:18"/> God, there he aſſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth him not with quenching the fire with water, but with working a wonder. For hee could both extinguiſh the fire, and diſtill downe a ſhowre from heauen, but this he doth not, leaſt he ſhould encreaſe the force of his rage, but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteth the flame to be made as great, as the furie of the tortor deſired, and hee doth not forbid him to puniſh, but taketh away power from the torment. And that no one that ſawe the children not burne, might ſuppoſe it was a vaine imagination, no fire in deede that he ſaw, he ſuffered the executioners (namely thoſe that ſtoode about the fornace) to bee conſumed, that hee might make manifeſt, that not onely fire in truth was ſeene, but that Gods commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was more forcible than any ſtrength of fire. For eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing that is, obeieth him of whom it had his begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:22457:18"/> That fire receiued the bodies of thoſe ſaints and by the ordinance and will of God forgetting his nature where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it burneth, vpon it ſhewed only his nature of illumining, rendring againe the holy and faithfull thing committed to his charge nothing hurted; for they came foorth out of the fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming fornace as it had beene out of a princes palace, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be admited of all, of all to be reuerenced. None then caſt his eyes on the king who glittered in purple, with a diademe on his head, but hee was forſaken of all, as though he had beene no body, for that the children had rapteu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> rich-one into an admiration. For who would not hee aſtonied that the fire was afrighted at the ſight of the young mens bodies, and that it did not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhe from the fleſh of thoſe ſaints, but alſo did not touch one haire of their head (which was but little) nor
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:22457:19"/> the vttermoſt hemine of their garments?</p>
                  <p>Who would not admire, that their members were ſtronger then mountains, their garments than mettals, their haires than diamonds? And herein is the wonder aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uated, that when they were in the middeſt of the fire, they ſang a Pſalme to God, albeit experience teacheth, that they that are committed to the flame, bee conſumed aſſoone as they open their mouth. To conclude theſe bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſed chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren remaine with God glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, with men wonderfull; but the naughtie king was neither mooued with theſe miracles, nor wondered at the viſion and the foretelling of his confuſion, but abode hard of beliefe, neither yet was puniſhed. And hitherto Gods patience was not tried, but when hee had forborne him a long time, at length hee vnneth corrected him, not pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:22457:19"/> the offences paſt, but reſpecting the amendment to come: in a word, he condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him not euerlaſtingly,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Dan.</hi> 4.33.</note> but chaſtiſed for a little ſpace, but reformed for a fewe yeeres he got againe his former eſtate, ſo that by the puniſhment he ſuſtained no loſſe but by the amendment gat great good.</p>
                  <p>Such (beleeue me) ſuch is the goodnes of God towards men, neuer reiecting repentance if it be truely and vprightly offred; although one come to the top of wickedneſſe,<note place="margin">Nunquam ſera eſt ad bonos mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res via. Sen.</note> notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding if he haue a deſire to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to the way of vertue, he gladly receiueth and imbraceth him, and doth all things wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he may be reclaimed to his wonted condition. Yea &amp; that which is more worth the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, although any be not able wholy to abandon the vre of ſin, he will not refuſe how ſmal ſoeuer repentance, &amp; in how little time ſoeuer vndertaken, hee will take it, and not ſuffer
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:22457:20"/> the leaſt conuerſion goe vnre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guerdoned.<note place="margin">Iſ. 57. Or, for his ſins I haue made him ſory a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle while, &amp;c. and I haue bin ſad, and I haue wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uily, and I haue hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him, I haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted him.</note> For this (mee thinketh) <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſheweth, where he ſpeaketh after this manner of the people of the Iewes, for his ſinne I haue made him ſomewhat ſory, and I haue ſmitten him, and I haue turned my face from him, and he was ſory and wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked heauily, and I healed him, and comforted him.</p>
                  <p>But the wicked king, that by reaſon of the naughtineſſe of his wife ſought a booty for his luſt, may be a more euident teſtimonie of this matter; who being troubled with the hainouſneſſe of his ſinnes, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented, and cloathed in ſacke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloth bewailed his doing, and heere in ſo drew the mercy of God vpon him, that hee par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned all his treſpaſſes. For ſo it is ſaid,<note n="*" place="margin">1. <hi>King.</hi> 21.28.29.</note> and the word of the Lord came to <hi>Eliah</hi> the Tiſhbite, ſaying, ſeeſt thou how <hi>Ahab</hi> is humbled before me? becauſe he ſubmitteth
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:22457:20"/> himſelfe before me, I will not bring that euill in his dayes. Alſo after him againe <hi>Manaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> who bare the bell from all pittileſſe tyrants, who ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threw the ſeruice of God and the worſhip of his lawes, who repleniſhed the Temple of the Lord with Idols, thruſting out the worſhipping of the Lord, this king (I ſay) ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſing the wickedneſſe that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer hath beene heard of, albeit repented, and after was num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred among the friends of God.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Chro.</hi> 33.</note> Now if he or they of whom afore we mentioned pondering the vnmeaſurable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of their tranſgreſſions, had deſpaired of returne by conuerſion and repentance, doubtles they had loſt all thoſe good things which happened vnto them by amendment of life. But contrariwiſe they beholding the mercy that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be vttered, and God his infinite and profound good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, vntied from their neckes
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:22457:21"/> the diueliſh bonds of deſpaire, and ſpurring vp themſelues, were conuerted to the way of vertue, and by withdrawing their foote from headlong ruine finiſhed a good courſe. And ſo farre of the examples of the holy men.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 95.1.</note>Now hearken how God by the Prophet allureth vs in words to repentance, to day (ſaith he) if you will heare his voice, harden not your hearts: &amp;c. And in that he ſaith to day, he meaneth all our life time, euen vnto the laſt part (if ſo it chaunce) of our olde age;<note place="margin">Short re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance looſeth not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. <hi>Ionas</hi> 3.</note> for not the length of time but the truenes of repenting is conſidered, or elſe how is it read that the Niniuites in the little ſpace of one day not in long time purged a moſt grieuous ſinne. And the theefe alſo which hanged on the croſſe,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luk.</hi> 23.</note> needed not a very long ſeaſon to bee made fit for para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, but ſo much ſpace was ynough as was ſpent in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:22457:21"/> one ſpeech Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that in a moment, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing all his ſinnes clenſed, he was thought worthy to enter heauen before euen the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles. And ſemblably, doe we not oftentimes ſee the martyrs in one day, and percaſe in the ſpace of one howre, to receiue the crownes of great rewards? Wherefore hardineſſe is all, and a boldnes conioined with p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ompt and ready minds, that mooued (as it were) with a certaine wrath, we be diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with luſt our inueagler, and offer all our deſire and loue on the altar of vertue. For this is that thing that God willeth, and requireth of vs, he ſeeketh not continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of time, nor vexation of vs, he reſpecteth true and vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fained conuerſion.<note n="*" place="margin">Seeing many that were laſt, haue by earneſt la our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded thoſe that were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> It is not then ſo badde to fall, as after a fall to lie ſtill, &amp; be vnwilling to riſe, couering the vitiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of our ill intent (taking no delight but in ſin) with deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:22457:22"/> ſpeeches For with indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation the Prophet crieth out againſt theſe; Doth not he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> riſe vp that falleth, and he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne that is turned away<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Jere.</hi> 8. Godly men may riſe by repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their fall.</note>?</p>
                  <p>Now if thou ſay; What if one of the faithfull ſhould fall. may he be reſtored? To this I aunſwere; in that we ſay he hath fallen, wee confeſſe he ſtood before he fell: for it is an abſurd thing to be ſpoken, that any man fell, that hath ſtill lien and neuer ſtood. We will produce alſo out of the booke of God allegations, if ought hath bene ſpoken of this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, either in parables or in plaine ſpeeches, or if any thing may be found in the examples of our elders. What repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth that ſheepe which when it wandred from the ninetie and nine,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luke</hi> 15.</note> was ſought by the ſheepheard, and brought home on his ſhoulders? doth it not euidently ſhew the ſliding and the repairing of a faithfull bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy? For it was a ſheepe like
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:22457:22"/> as were the ninety and nine, not of any other, but of the ſelfe ſame flocke, it had the ſelfe ſame guides, it was firſt fed in the ſame paſture, with the ſame water, and the ſame fold contained it that did the reſt. But it ſtraied not a litle, and wandred through the mountaines and hils, that is, it went farre from the right path, yet the good ſheepheard ſuffereth it not to pine away in ſtraying, but ſeeketh it, and calleth it againe, and he calleth it home, not driuing it vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently, neither beating it with ſtrokes, but ſupporting it with his owne ſhoulders. For as all ſkillull Phyſitions by mitigation of medicine deale more nicely and tenderly, with thoſe that haue beene long vexed with infirmitie: ſo God doth not reclaime thoſe that haue beene long corrupt with ſinne to the way of vertue with any tariance at all, but by peece-meale, and little and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:22457:23"/> little, bearing with their weakeneſſe in many things, and aſſiſting them often, that conuerſion on the ſudden may not be vnpleaſant to them, and that they may not goe againe to lewdnes, for the difficulty of returning.</p>
                  <p>But not this parable onely declareth the moderateneſſe of alteration, but that likewiſe which is written of the prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall ſonne.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luke</hi> 15.</note> He was a ſonne alſo no aliant, his naturall brother that neuer went from his father: he (I ſay) was a ſonne that went far in the bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of iniquitie: for he went into a farre countrey, and farre from the Lord, he that was rich and of good name, was made baſer then a ſeruant and hireling, but ſorrowfully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning, he was taken into his ancient eſtate and inueſted in his former glorie: Now if he had loſt hope, and had beene aſhamed to come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to his father, becauſe of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:22457:23"/> his miſchanches, and had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ode alway in a ſtraunge and forren countrey, hee had not gotten that he gat, but peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing for want of food, had di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a miſerable death. You ſee therefore how great neceſſitie repentance hath, what force in turning hope hath, by repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance the prodigall ſonne re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered the olde condition of his glory, which the elder brother had without repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. And if I might ſpeake that I would in theſe matters, me ſeemeth he gat more by conuerſion than the other had.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>ver.</hi> 26.30.</note> For ſo he himſelfe ſaith, loe theſe many yeeres haue I done thee ſeruice, and yet thou neuer gaueſt me a kid that I might make mery with my friends.<note place="margin">Sinners conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted get more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they which ſtumbled not.</note> But when this thy ſonne was come, which hath deuoured thy goods with harlots, thou haſt for his ſake killed the fat calfe. Why ſhould I not then think, that he that turneth by repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:22457:24"/> obtaineth more then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſith he had neuer a kid gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen him, but for this the fat calfe was killed? Wherefore beloued hauing theſe examples of repentance, let vs not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in euils, nor deſpaire of at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonement: he will neuer (put affiance in me) turne his eyes from the conuerted, if we our ſelues remooue not our ſelues from God.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Hier.</hi> 23.23. Our ſins ſeparate vs from God. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 59.2.</note> For he ſaith, I am a God at hand, and not a God farre off. And againe by the Prophet,<note n="*" place="margin">Or your iniquities haue ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated betweene you and your God</note> Your ſinnes ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate betweene me and you. If then our ſinnes diſſeuer vs from God, let vs take away this barre, and nothing may let vs to be brought into the fauour of God.</p>
                  <p>Will you that I ſhew it not onely ſpoken in parables, but formed in deed? There was a man among the Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans by all likelihood of no ſmall calling, he had commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſuch a ſinne, as was not committed amongſt the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:22457:24"/> being of the numbe of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he faithfull, and Chriſts his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>riends, for ſome report (mee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hinketh) that he was of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mage of the Prieſts. What <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hen? <hi>Paul</hi> neuer parted him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rom the number of thoſe, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ope to attaine ſaluation. But when he had ſufficiently rebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed the Corinthians for him, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>urpoſing to ſhew that there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s no wound nor diſeaſe, that may not bee cured and made whole by repentance he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth to deliuer him ouer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nto Sathan,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.5.</note> for the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tion of the fleſh, that the ſpirit may be ſaued in the day of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ord Ieſus. But this he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth before he was done <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o wit of his repentance; for when he had ſorowed, it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ufficient (ſaith he) to him,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.6.</note> that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e hath beene rebuked of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and addeth,<note place="margin">8.</note> Wherefore I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ray you that you would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>irme your loue towards him: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſt Sathan ſhould circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ent vs,<note place="margin">11.</note> for we are not igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:22457:25"/> of his enterpriſes. The nation of the Galathians af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it had perfectly beleeued in Chriſt, and had receiued the holy Ghoſt, inſomuch that it wrought ſignes and miracles by the ſpirit, after, for the faith of Chriſt it had ſuſteined ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things, after al theſe things (I ſay) it fell from the faith, and was renued againe by the exhortations of the Apoſtle. And that thou maiſt know that by the ſpirit they had done wonders and miracles, heare howe the Apoſtle ſaith: hee therfore that miniſtreth to you the ſpirit,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.5.</note> and worketh mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles among you, doth he it by the workes of the law, or by the hearing of faith preached? And againe, that they had ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteined many things after the receit of faith, he teſtifieth where he ſaith:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſ.</hi> 4.</note> Haue you ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered ſo many things in vaine? Now after ſo great a ſteppe in faith they committed a ſinne which was able to abalienate
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:22457:25"/> them from Chriſt, of which the Apoſtle himſelfe ſaith:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.2.</note> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold I <hi>Paul</hi> ſay vnto you, that if you be circumciſed, Chriſt ſhall profite you nothing. And againe,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſe</hi> 4.</note> whoſoeuer are iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by the law, yee are fallen from grace. And notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding after theſe ſlides in faith after ſo grieuous a fall, hee reclaimeth them, and (as I may ſay) with motherlike compaſſion reformeth them, ſaying: My little children,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.19.</note> of whom I trauell in birth againe, vntill Chriſt be formed in you.</p>
                  <p>What elſe therefore by all this is there taught, but that it may be, that Chriſt may be formed anew in him, that hath ſolde himſelfe to worke iniquitie, for he will not the death of a ſinner,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eze.</hi> 18.32</note> but that he ſhould be conuerted and liue. For this cauſe (moſt intirely beloued) let vs goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to fulfill the will of God, therefore hath God created
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:22457:26"/> vs, and cauſed vs to be that we were not, that he may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow euerlaſting good things vpon vs,<note place="margin">Heauen was made for man, hell for the diuils.</note> and enfranchiſe vs into the heauenly city, for hee made vs not faggots for hell fire. The kingdome of heauen was ordained for vs, and hell for the diuell. And that this is true, the Goſpell teacheth: for the Lord ſhall ſay to them on his right hand,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.34.</note> Come ye bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of my father, inherite yee the kingdome prepared for you from the foundation of the world.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſ.</hi> 42.</note> But hee ſhall ſay to them on his left hand, depart from mee yee curſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d into euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting fire, which is prepared for the diuell and his Angels By this reaſon the kingdome of heauen was made for man and hell fire for the diuell, euen from the foundation of the world.</p>
                  <p>So much doth it concerne vs, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> by preſeruering in euils, wee doe not frowardly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude our ſelues from the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:22457:26"/> of goodnes.<note place="margin">Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance in this life profiteth much, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this life nought.</note> And while we are in this life how great ſoeuer ſinnes we commit, it is poſſible by repentance to purge them: but when we are once dead, then though we ſorrie (and we ſhalbe very be ſorrie) yet there will bee no profite of repentance. Although there be gnaſhing of teeth although there be howling and lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, although we pray and begge with innumerable peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, yet none ſhall heare vs, none ſhall helpe vs, no not our tongue torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted in flames ſhall be wet with the tippe of a finger dipped in water. But we ſhall heare that which the rich man heard of <hi>Abraham,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luke</hi> 16.26.</note> that there is a great ſwallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing pitte ſet betweene vs and you ſo that they which would goe from hence to you cannot: neither can they come from thence to vs. Therfore let vs repent (my brother) and as good and profitable ſeruants ſeeke our Lord Ieſus Chriſt,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:22457:27"/> neither let vs be diſcouraged to obtaine pardon (while we liue here) by repentance, for in hell (as I ſaid) the medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines of repentance will not be auaileable, but in this life, though in the ende of your dayes and extreme old age you vſe it, it ſhall cure you. Which to ſtoppe, the diuell ſtarreth and laboureth, that hee may make vs deſpaire, for hee knoweth that euen in a little time, if any be penitent, though it be a ſhort turn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ng, yet it wil not be vnfruitfull. For as the man that giueth a cuppe of cold water looſeth not his meed; ſo he that hath remorſe for his euill deedes, though his repentance ſeeme not counter-poyſable to his offences, yet howe little ſoeuer it bee, and in the twinkling of an eye, the recompence ſhall not bee lacking. No one good deed though very ſmall, ſhall bee contemned of the Lord a iuſt iudge: for if he be ſo harde a
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:22457:27"/> computiſt of our miſdeedes, as that euery one muſt be puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed for his wordes and thoughts,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.</note> how much more ſhall nor good deeds both great and ſmall be rewarded in the day of doome? Wherefore if thou thinke it vnpoſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ble to be reſtored to thy accuſtomed or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of life, yet prune off a little from that great extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of ryot and luſt, which thou ſhalt perceiue not a whit vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fructuous. Make onely a beginning and ſmoth the way to goodneſſe, which tread, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit with the tips of thy toes; and till thou begin, the way of vertue ſeemeth difficile and hard. For ſuch is the nature of all things, that all labour is thought grieuous while it is weighed only in our minds, but when we come to the matter and haue ouercom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med ſome of the worke, then all feare and fainting is ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken off, and the ſucceſſe of the worke breedeth delight:
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:22457:28"/> ſo alſo the renuing of vertue cauſeth gladneſſe to the mind, and then are wee ſtronger, when we ſee the hope of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation approch.</p>
                  <p>For this cauſe alſo the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie tooke <hi>Iudas</hi> hence, leaſt in caſe knowing there was a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to ſaluation, he might reforme his fall by repentance. And I ſay not (although it be wonderfull) that that ſinne of <hi>Iudas</hi> might not be purged by repentance: for which cauſe I intreat and begge of thee that thou abandon out of thy mind all diueliſh cogitations, and quickly return thee to the way of ſaluation. If I ſhould ſodainely &amp; wholy call thee to that old height of vertue, thou mighteſt not without cauſe tremble, not without reaſon d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ement hard. But conſidering this only I deſire at thy hands, that thou increaſe not in ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, neither euery day goe neerer to perdition, that thou leaue off and make an end of
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:22457:28"/> offending, why doeſt thou doubt and linger, drawing backe thy foote, for feare onely to receiue the thought of good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe? Hath not the ſuperflui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of luſt bred loathſomneſſe, as yet in thee? What hath it bettered them that abode in bodily ſenſualitie and in the pleaſures of this preſent life vntill the end of their liues?<note place="margin">Pleaſure of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy vadeth away.</note> Looke nowe on their ſepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, and ſee whither there be any ſhew of glorious iollitie? Whether there be any token of dainties and ſumptuous fare. Demaund where nowe their gorgeous weedes and ſtrange perfumes bee, whither the pleaſure of their games, the troupes of their attendants, the daintines of their feaſts is gone? Whither their laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures ſports, immoderate and vnbrideled luſt is become and vaniſhed? Where they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues are with all theſe things? What was the end of them both? Behold more
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:22457:29"/> narrowly and come more neere to their graues, looke on the duſt onely and the filthie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques of wormes, remember that this is the end of bodies, although in delights and ioy, although in labour and chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie men ſpend their life. And would God all the matter were ended in duſt &amp; wormes, theſe loſſes would ſeeme but little, and the ſtate of nature mought eaſily be excuſed But now gl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e thine eyes from theſe aſhes and graues,<note place="margin">How ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ible the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>udgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eate of God ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e to the wicked.</note> and thinke vpon, that horrible ſeat of the iudgement of God, which is inuironed with a burning riuer of fierie ſtreams where is weeping and gna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of teeth, where is vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter darkeneſſe, where is that worme of conſcience that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th, and the vnquencha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble fire Forget not the para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of <hi>Lazarus</hi> &amp; the rich man,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>uk.</hi> 16.</note> who being once an owner of great wealth, and clad in purple and ſilke, could not find
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:22457:29"/> (afterward) one drop of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and that when hee was in the heat of the fire. Tell me (I beſeech thee) what is there in this lif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> but a dreame?<note place="margin">Our life but a dreame.</note> For as thoſe that are condemned to liue among mettals, or afflicted with any other puniſhment, when they take ſome reſt, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the hard labours of their troubleſome life, beleeue them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to enioy the manifold dainties they ſee before them; but when they ariſe they ſeele ful wel, there is nothing left of the delicatenes of the dreame. ſo the rich man who in a dream had the voluptuouſnes of this life, when he deceaſed, nought remained with him but griefe of the thinges paſt, and paine of the thinges preſent. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member this (my friend) and oppoſe hell fire to this flame of luſt and concupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcence that now tormenteth thee. And it is a ſtrang kind of medicine that fire ſhou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d bee quenched by fire; but if this
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:22457:30"/> fire ſhall not bee ſtinted which now ſo troubleth thee, it will cauſe to thee that euer-endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring fire more fierce and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenchable.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ures of this life are mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentarie, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n reſpect of the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment for them.</note>Alſo, how long doeſt thou iudge the pleaſures of thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent life may endure? As I thinke thou canſt not liue 50. yeeres moe, admit thy old age be long. But in the meane while ſee what things befall, firſt in this behalfe, that no body is certaine he may liue till night; next, for that the condition of humane affaires is ſtill moueable, for many times life continueth many yeeres, but wealth and riches fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>le, and often ſome make ſhippewracke of goods be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they die. But grant we, that thou mayeſt both liue along time, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer no al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eration of times; yet what is this ſpace to euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting paines; what is this voluptie to thoſe miſerable and vntollerable plagues? For
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:22457:30"/> in this life whether it bee good or euill, it hath his limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and that ſpeedily but in the world to come both are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting. Ouer and beſides, the ſtate of the very puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is different: for the fire in this life conſumeth all things it taketh, but that fire whom it once taketh hold on, it vex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th and alwayes reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth to the torment. And therefore it is termed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenchable, not onely becauſe it cannot be quenched it ſelfe, but b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cauſe it doth not quench or ſley them it taketh. For the Scripture ſaith, that ſinners put on immortalitie, to wit, profitable, not to honour of life, but to perpetuitie of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.</p>
                  <p>Now the force of the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, and that puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of that fire which is ſo forcibl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o voice will ſerue to declare, no ſpeech will ſerue to vtter: for in good or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill things ſubiect to corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:22457:31"/> there is nothing like them. Neuertheleſſe that wee may conceiue ſome motion of that fire and torment,<note place="margin">The tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of hell ſet foorth in their co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours.</note> call to mind, in him that hath a burning ague, what tribulation, what anxietie of the bodie and ſoule ſtandeth on each ſide, and by this temporall maladie ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther what thoſe torments be which are inflamed with an eternall fire, which are wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered before that horrible iudgem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nt ſ at with a fierie ſtreame of tormenting waues. There what ſhall wee doe? What ſhall we anſwere? No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſhall be t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ere but gna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eth, but ſchritching and weeping, and too to late repentance, no way any helpe being found, and euery way the torments increaſing with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any comfort. Wee ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ee none but the executioners and tortors dreadfull to bee beholden, and (which is woorſt of all) we ſhall haue no ſolace of the very aire. For vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:22457:31"/> darknes ſhall compaſſe the place of torments, and the fire which as it hath not a nature of conſuming, ſo hath it not of illumining, but it is a darke fire, the flame thereof giuing no light. So that to them that are in it, what feare what renting of their bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els, what diſmembring of their bodies, what croſſes there be to euery ſenſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> no tongue can tell. And as the ſortes of tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments doe varie and differ, ſo proportionably euerich one to his ſinnes hath his paine mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplied.</p>
                  <p>Now if thou ſhouldeſt ſay, how can the bodie continue in ſo wretched and ſuch an end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe tormenting? Conſider what things now and then in this life betide vs, and by theſe ſmall things coniecture great, How that ſome times we ſee ſome troubled with long ſicknes, &amp; yet their life to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure: and howbeit the bodie bee diſſolued by ſome death,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:22457:32"/> yet the ſoule is not diſſolued nor conſumed: whence it is apparant that when the body ſhall alſo become immortall, no death may kill the ſoule or body. For in this preſent life it cannot be, that the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the body ſhould bée both grieuous and perpetuall, but the one yeeldeth to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for that the body cannot abide both But when each ſhall put off corruption, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> corruption afore receiued ſhall end, but the incorruption got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſhall be endleſſe. So let vs not thinke the very exceeding greatneſſe of puniſhment will cauſe an end of dolor, but (as I ſaid) our ſinnes ſhall ag<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>grauate the chaſtiſement, and the incorruption of the bodie or ſoule ſhall not limite it.</p>
                  <p>Tell mee now, what ſpace of ſenſualitie and dainties will thou liken to theſe torments? Let vs (if we liſt) beſtow on delights an hundreth yeeres, adde thereto an hundreth moe,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:22457:32"/> and tenne times an hundreth, what benefit will there be got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of it, if we conſider this e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer-remaining paine? May not the whole time of this life, wherein wee ſeeme to take pleaſure in paſtimes, and wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low in wantonneſſe, be recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned as the dreame of one night, in compariſon of that eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie? Is there any therefore, who to haue a delightſome dreame one night, would vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake ſempiternall paines? Or take that for this, or this for that?</p>
                  <p>I diſprayſe not as yet de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights, nor vnfolde the bitter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe of them, becauſe the time ſerueth not for ſuch ſpeeches nowe, but then I ſhall be oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned, when I ſee thee able to auoid the ſame. For be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou art addicted to them, thou mayeſt gheſſe wee doted, if we auouch that plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure which all men reckon ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable and gladſome, were yrkeſome and ſowre: But if
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:22457:33"/> by the mercy of God, thou maieſt eſcape out of this ſort of ſickenes, at that time, yea at that time thou ſhalt finde out what bitterneſſe, yea what bane ſenſualitie hath. Nowe m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ane while let vs imagine, that paſtimes and pleaſure and voluptuouſneſſe are ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and comely: What ſhall we ſay to the puniſhments laide vp in ſtore for them? What ſhall we ſay to them, becauſe the delights vade like a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, and haſtily flie away, but the paine abideth for eu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r and euer?</p>
                  <p>Grant the time and ſpace of paſtime and puniſhment were all one, is there any ſo fooliſh, or ſo depriued of his fiue wits, that would chuſe to tolerate one day of paine for a day of pleaſure? ſith the pangs of one houre, and euery vexation of the body, commonly cauſeth vs to forget all the time paſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed in delight. Wherefore foraſmuch as we may be ridde
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:22457:33"/> (if in a moment we be turned) from euery of thoſe tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting chaſtiſements, and inioy eternall goodnes, why deferre we? why ſtay we? why doe we not vſe the bountifulneſſe of God? For this is prouided by the vnſpeakeable and infinite clemencie of God, that labour and toile ſhould not bee ſtret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched farre, nor be long or end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe but ſhort, and (as I may ſay) for a minute of an houre. Such is this preſent life, if it be conferred with that euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.</note> The clemency (I ſay) of God hath prouided, that in this fleeting &amp; ſhort life, there ſhould be labors and agonies, but that in the life eternall, there ſhould be crownes &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards of good workes, &amp; that trauell ſhould ſoone be ended, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ut the reward of good deeds ſhould laſt for euer. And euen as this maketh them glad that through induring of toile in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioye a crowne: ſo it ſhall grieue and trouble thoſe in the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:22457:34"/> time to come, that ſee they haue loſt (for a little and ſmall time of delights) perpetuall good things, and haue ſought for ſtill induring euill things.</p>
                  <p>Let vs not therefore incurre this anguiſh of ſoule, let vs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake while wee haue time. And loe now is the acceptable time, now is the day of ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, now is opportunitie of repentance, and a time where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in repentance will not be fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe. But if we be careleſſe of our life, wee ſhall ſuſtaine in hell not theſe calamities alone, whereof we haue ſpoken, but a more grieuous miſchiefe. For to be excluded from bliſſe, and to be debarred from the things prepared for the Saincts, cauſeth ſuch afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſuch wofulneſſe, as (if no outward puniſhment tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) it were ſufficient. It ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſeth all paines of hell, to want that beatitude, the frui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of which lay in thy pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. For muſe (I deſire you)
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:22457:34"/> on the ſtate of that life,<note place="margin">Heauenly bliſſe ſet foorth.</note> as much as a man may conſider <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t, for as it is in deed, no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>peech can vtter. Yet let vs comprehend an image thereof, to the vtmoſt it may be, by that we haue read, and the darke ſpeeches we haue recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. It is ſaid of it in a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine place,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Reu.</hi> 21.4. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 35.</note> There ſhall be no more death, neither ſorrowe, neither crying, neither ſhall there be any more paine. What more felicitie is there than this life, wherin no feare of pouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, nor ſickeneſſe hurteth, none dealeth vniuſtly, none is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dangered, none conceiueth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation, none enuieth, no deſire inflameth, no luſt of meat, no greedineſſe of honour and renowne troubleth: but euery ſpot of vice is blotted out and waſhed away, where all things are in peace and ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, all things in quiet and reſt, where is light and brightneſſe, not ſuch as is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong vs, but by ſo much
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:22457:35"/> more bright the ſunne is now than any candle? There is no night, no darkeneſſe, no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of clouds, no extremity of cold or heate; but ſuch a temperature ſhall there bee of all things, as they alone ſhall know which are worthy to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy the ſame. There is no old age, nor the miſerie thereof, but euery corru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tible thing is done away, and the glory of incorruption is euery where But moreouer to haue ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie with the Angels &amp; Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angels, and of all the celeſtiall and ſupernall powers to inioy the companie, is much to bee eſteemed: but to obtaine the radiant ſight of our Lorde Chriſt Ieſus, and to be ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tened with the brightneſſe of his maieſty, that cannot be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, it paſſeth all ſuch and ſuch like honour.</p>
                  <p>But leſt thou bee daunted with theſe thinges on the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine, I will allure thee by lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle and little to the attain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:22457:35"/> of them. Behold now and looke vpon the heauen, let thy thought alſo pierce a little aboue heauen, after yonder the tranſforming of the whole creature. For it ſhall not abide in this qualitie wherein it is, but it ſhall be chaunged into another much more fine and faire, as much (let me ſay ſo) as gold excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth lead. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth this ſhall come to paſſe, when he ſaith that the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture it ſelfe ſhall be freed from the bondage of corruption.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.21.</note> For now vnder corruption it ſuffereth many things which corruptible bodies muſt needs ſuffer: but when it ſhall caſt off all frailetie and corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it ſhall be adorned with wonderfull beautie, for it ſhall not ſuffer corruptible bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, but it ſhall receiue them (by reſurrection) uoyde of corruption, whereby the very creature ſhall bee metamor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſed into an excellenter ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite.
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:22457:36"/> There ſhall bee then no diſſention any where, but all things ſhall agree in amitie, for the agreement of the ſaints ſhall be one, there ſhall be no dread of the Diuell, no am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſhes of vncleane ſpirits, the teare of hell ſhall be farre off, there ſhall be death neither of the body, nor of the ſoule, but feare by the meanes of immortalitie ſhall bee ſhaken off.</p>
                  <p>Like as a kings ſonne if firſt of all he be foſtered vp in a poore cottage being apparal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in baſe raiment, liueth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the feare of Tutors, and gouernance of Maſters, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by his young-age vnder ſtrait diſcipline may bring his mans eſtate into good liking, and make it worthy his famous progenitors; but when the time commeth, that he muſt both enter into the Court of his Dominion, and take in hand his fathers Scepter, all homely apparaile being reie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:22457:36"/> hee arayeth himſelfe in princely attire, and on a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aine putteth on the mitre of his father, the glittering of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>urple continually is added, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he brightneſſe of his diademe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he rowte of his gard, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ower of his name is increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed, and he is made a new man, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o after ſuch a manner ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he alteration of Saints be.</p>
                  <p>And to the end you may be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iuen to vnderſtand, that pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed words is not all we ſpeake, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>et vs caſt our eyes on that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ountaine wherein Chriſt was tranſformed, and let vs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ehold his brightneſſe, that wherein (when he was tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ormed) hee ſhined; neither <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>or all that by this meanes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll the glory of the world to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ome ſhalbe reuealed vnto vs. For that tranſformation was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eclared not fully as in deede <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he bleſſedneſſe to come ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, but as much as the behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ers eyes could beare. And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he Goſpell ſaith<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 17.2.</note> his face did
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:22457:37"/> ſhine as the ſunne: but the glory of the incorruption ſhall not onely ſend foorth ſuch a light, nor ſuch as the eyes of men can looke on, but ſuch ſhal be the future brightneſſe, as eye ſight may not indure, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it abode that in the tranſforming on the mount. Whereby it is cleere, that ſo much was reuealed as the eies of mortall men could ſuffer neither yet did they fully ſuffer it,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſe</hi> 6.</note> for it is ſaid, They fell on their faces.</p>
                  <p>Againe, if thou ſhouldeſt be brought into an aſſemble, where euery one ſhould ſit ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parrelled in golden robes, in the middeſt of whom one ſhould ſhine decked in pearles and purple, and if he promiſed that thou mighteſt be one of the number of thoſe men of honour, wouldeſt thou not aſſay and attempt all things to attaine vnto it? So then open thy ſight on the heauens, and behold there an aſſembly ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:22457:37"/> together, not in bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of gold, neither in trim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of garments, nor gliſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in precious ſtones, but clearer in righteouſnes then either the ſtarres glitter, or the Sunne ſhineth. Behold there a company not of men a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, but of Angels, Archan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels thrones, dominions, prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalities, and powers; and of the King that ſitteth in the middeſt of them, no ſpeech may be, for he ſurmounteth all ſpeech and conceit of the mind of man, by reaſon of his beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, his ſtrength, his glory, his royalty, his maieſtie, What then? Tell me, ſhall we beguile our ſelues of all theſe honors, becauſe of ſloth in ſuſtaining ſome labour, and in reſiſting for a while the allurements of luſt? For if wee ſhould dayly ſuſtaine torments, and ſuffer a little time hell fire to the end we might ſee Chriſt comming in glory, &amp; accompanied with his Saints, were it not good
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:22457:38"/> to indure all ſorrow, that we might be made partakers of ſo great bliſſe, of ſo great glory? Heare what the bleſſed Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith;<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Matt.</hi> 17.4</note> It is good for vs to to be heer. If he ſeeing a ſlender glimſe of the glory to come ſodainely reiected all things out of his mind, rely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the delectation of the viſion he ſaw, what will one ſay, if he beheld theſe things, as they are in truth? Namely at what time, the court of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſhall bee opened, and the K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ng of heauen ſhall be reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, not in a glaſſe darkely, but face to face, not by faith, but by viſage.</p>
                  <p>Many ignorant folke think it a thing all ſuffici<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nt,<note place="margin">The tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of hell not ſo gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous as the loſſe of the ſight of Chriſt.</note> and to be wiſhed for, alone to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered from the paines of hel; I ſay to be remooued and caſt off from that glory, is a more grieuous torment then hell: neither iudge I the torm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nts there ſo grieuous, as it is to be driuen from the ſight of
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:22457:38"/> Chriſt for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s (I aſſure you) is more miſerable then any pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, this onely exceedeth hell When we ſee an earthly king entring his pallace, with his adherents and guard, we admire, and call thoſe great men who waite vpon him, and ſuppoſe our ſelues wretched, if we bee not vouchſafed any place amongſt them: though we know the weaknes and inſtability of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe terrene things, ſomtimes for forreine warres, ſometimes for ciuill conterwaits, and ſometimes for malicious ſpite, yet howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer it bee, it grieueth thoſe that haue fallen thence. How then ſhall it not much more vexe vs, if with the higheſt king, who holdeth the whole globe of the earth,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iſai.</hi> 40.</note> (not a part thereof onely) yea, who hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it in his fiſt, who meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the heauen with an hand breadth, who ſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth each thing by the word of his power who reckoneth the
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:22457:39"/> Gentiles as nothing, yea as ſpettle, with this (I ſay) when he beſtoweth honour that ſhal laſt for euer, we haue no place, neither be numbred among his ſeruants? Will it not pinch vs more then any paine?</p>
                  <p>But peraduenture thou ſayeſt, it will ſuffice vs to eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape hell, albeit wee bee not thought worthy of the ſight of the King. What more vnhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py and wretched ſoule is there than to which this is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent? Suppoſeſt thou that the King wherof we ſpeake, ſhall come to iudge the earth, carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Chariots of Mules, or in gilded waggons, or with the terrible power of a dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deme? Nay harken how the Prophets foretold (as much as might be declared to men) the comming of Chriſt. One of them ſaith thus: Our God ſhall come,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.3.</note> and ſhall not keepe ſilence, a fire ſhall deuour be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, and a mighty tempeſt ſhall be mooued round about
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:22457:39"/> him, he ſhall call the heauen aboue, and the earth to iudge his people. And harken how another to wit, <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the diuerſe ſorts of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ments; theſe are his wordes; Behold the day of the Lord commeth, cruel, with wrath,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iſai.</hi> 13.9.</note> and firce anger to lay the land waſt; and he ſhall deſtroy the ſinners out of it. For the ſtarres of heauen,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſe.</hi> 10.</note> and the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets thereof, ſhall not giue their light, the Sunne ſhall be darkened in his going forth, and the Moone ſhall not cauſe her light to ſhine,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſe.</hi> 11.</note> And I will viſit the wickednes vpon the world, and their iniquitie vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the wicked, and I wil cauſe the arrogancy of the proud to ceaſe. I will make a man more precious then fine Gold,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſe.</hi> 12.</note> euen a man aboue the wedge of gold of Ophir.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſe.</hi> 13.</note> Therefore I will ſhake the heauen, and the earth ſhall remooue out of her place, in the wrath of the Lord of hoaſts, and in the day of his
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:22457:40"/> fierce anger. And againe hee ſaith the windowes from on high are open,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Jſa.</hi> 24.18.</note> and the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations of the earth doe ſhake. The earth is vtterly broken downe,<note place="margin">19.</note> the earth is cleane diſſolued, the earth is exceeding<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly mooued. The earth ſhall reele too and fro like a drunken man,<note place="margin">20.</note> and ſhall be remoued like a tent, the iniquity thereof ſhal be heauy vpon it ſo that it ſhal fall and riſe no more. And in that day,<note place="margin">21.</note> ſhal the Lord viſit the hoa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t aboue, that is on high, euen the Kings of the world that are vpon the earth and they ſhal be gathered together as the priſoners in the pit, and they ſhall be ſhut vp in priſon. And the Prophet <hi>Malachies</hi> words are conſonant hereto;<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Malac.</hi> 3. <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſe</hi> 1.2.</note> Behold he ſhall come ſaith the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ord of hoaſts, But who may abide the day of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming? and who ſhall indure when he appeareth? For he is like a purging fire, and like fullers ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pe.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſe</hi> 3.</note> And hee ſhall ſit
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:22457:40"/> downe to fine and try the ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, he ſhall euen fine the ſons of <hi>Leuie</hi> and purifie them as gold and ſiluer.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 4.1.</note> And againe he ſaith, for behold the day com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth that ſhall burne as an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and all the proud yea; and all that doe wickedly ſhall bee as ſtable, and the day that com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>meth ſhall burne them vp, ſaith the Lord of hoaſts, and ſhall leaue them neither roote nor branch. And another of the Prophets ſaith,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.9.</note> I beheld till the thrones were ſet vp, and the auncient of daies did ſit, whoſe garment was white as ſnow, and the haire of his head like pure wooll.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſe.</hi> 10</note> A fiery ſtreame iſſued and came forth from before him, the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was ſet, and the bookes opened. And a little after,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſ.</hi> 13.</note> as I beheld in viſions by night, beholde one like the ſonne of man, came in the cloudes of heauen, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached vnto the aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent of theſe dayes, and
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:22457:41" rendition="simple:additions"/> they brought him before him. And he gaue him dominion,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſ.</hi> 14.</note> and honour, and a Kingdome, that all people, nations and languages, ſhould ſerue him, his dominion is an euerlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing dominion, which ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be taken away, and his kingdome ſhall neuer bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſ.</hi> 15.</note> I <hi>Daniel</hi> was trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in my ſpirit, in the midſt of my body, and the viſions of mine head made me afraid.</p>
                  <p>So then when theſe things ſhall begin, the gates of heauen ſhall be opened yea rather the very heauen ſhall be taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, as if the couerings of a pauilion were drawne toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to wit, that it may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored and tranſfigured into better. Then all things ſhall be in feare, amazedneſſe and trembling ſhall fill euery place. Then alſo feare ſhall ſhake the Angels, and not the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels alone, but perchance the Archangels, thrones, domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, rules and powers. For
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:22457:41"/> this is ſignified where it is ſaid I will ſhake the heauen;<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Jſai.</hi> 13.13</note> for they are the fellow ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants of them that muſt bee iudged and muſt giue an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of this life. If when one Citie is to bee iudged by the iudges of this world other feare and ſhake although it be not for great danger like to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue when the vniuerſal world ſhall come to be iudged of him that lacketh not witneſſe, that doth not ſeek arguments, that doth not require an orator for the cauſe, but all theſe things being remooued, that doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueale the deeds, wordes, and thoughts of men, that placeth each thing in open ſight, and heweth euery fact, as it wrre in a painted table, before the eyes, both of the tranſgreſſors and the beholders, how much more ſhall euery creature bee mooued with feare? And if then no fierie ſtreame ſhould iſſue forth neither the terrible Angels, or greeſely executio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:22457:42"/> ſhould ſtand by; but if thus onely it were, that men ſhould be called, before the king and ſome ſhould be pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and honoured, other ſome without honour caſt to confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; if men did onely ſuffer this puniſhment, would it not ſurpaſſe the torments of hell, that when other were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed with gifts of the king, they ſhould ſhamefully ſuffer the repulſe? Which paine how vntolerable it is, although ſpeech now may not declare, yet then ſhall we cleerely per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue it, when we come to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience.</p>
                  <p>Furthermore, beſides all theſe anguiſhes of torments fet before your eyes. not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion alone, and vtter ſhame but the way how men are drawne to fire, and deliuered vp to racking. Thinke vpon thoſe cruell and vgly tortors which throw ſinners downe headlong and in that time, in which other that haue done
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:22457:42"/> well, by the bright and gentle Angels being caried before the high throne of the euerlaſting king ſhall be rewarded with immortall gifte.</p>
                  <p>Theſe things are accidents to that day, iudgement, &amp; time, but that which enſueth, what tong can tell? What pleaſure, what ioy ſhall it be to be with Chriſt, when the ſoule cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to her proper vigor, ſhall with confidence begin to looke on God? none can declare the greatnes of that ioy. For ſhe triumpheth not alone for the fruit: on of the things pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, but ſhee reioyceth much more becauſe ſhee knoweth, there ſhall be no end of her bleſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſednes. And howbeit no ſpeech can ſet forth that gladnes and mirth, nor any thought o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taine it yet ſeeing (as it were) a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſhadow of the thing to come, we will alſo endeuour to acquaint you with it Demand we of the rich &amp; welthy of this world. who vaunt in honors &amp;
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:22457:43"/> power, with what gladneſſe they are puffed out? With how great delectation and pleaſure they are in loue with theſe things, ſo that ſometime they carry their noſes very high in the wind? And that, though they themſelues know, that theſe things are neither right, happy, nor yet euerlaſting, but vaniſh away ſooner then a dreame: which if they indure while this life remaineth, if we make the moſt of them we can, they can indure no longer. Wherefore if men are ſo excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ioyous, for fraile and tranſitory things with what ioy ſhall wee thinke thoſe ſoules to be filled, which haue gotten heauenly and eternall b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſe? In which both quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and quallity differeth ſo much from the other in excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency, (for all that in this life we account them good) ſo that neither eye hath ſeene,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iſai.</hi> 64.4 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.9.</note> nor eare hath heard, nor heart as yet hath vnderſtood them. For as
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:22457:43"/> a little one is in the belly of his mother; ſo are we in the world in wrapped ſtraitely in darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and cannot behold the light and liberty of the world to come. But when the time ſhall come,<note place="margin">Such corne as we ſow here, ſuch bread ſhal wee eate in the world to come.</note> that this world ſhal trauell in birth with vs, and ſhal bring forth into the brigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the future world all it hath conceiued if any ſhall bee found (by the meanes of ſinne) putrified or not of full growth they goe from darkenes to harkenes, from tribulation to more bitter tribulation. But they that ſhall be perfect and like vnto the king, ſhe proffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to the father, as a worthy iſſue to be placed in the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of Angels, and in the ſeates of Archangels.</p>
                  <p>Therfore will you goe that way (my friend) that the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, and kingly beauty of thy ſoule may bee polluted and this world at the laſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectt thee, but repaire quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Image of thy father, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:22457:44"/> thy vertue, beauty, and gallantnes, that among other thou mayeſt be knowne of thy father.<note place="margin">The ſoule muſt be polliſhed more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the body and God hath thus appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note> The beauty of the body, God hath limited with certaine naturall bonds. but the beauty of the ſoule he hath made free, and ſubiect to no neceſſity which leaueth far behind the comlines of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. Inſomuch that the trim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of our ſoule is at the back of God, yet in our power. For if the Lord had graunted vs licence to vſe our owne fan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy in our bodilie brauery, we ſhould haue beene burdened with ſuperfluous and naught inaileable cares, ſpending all the time of our life in them, whereby the ſoule muſt needes not be docked Sith euen now when we haue no power ouer the trimnes of our bodies, we ſo carke and care, that by all poſſible meanes we poliſh them, aſſaying by the painting of colours, by the friſling of our haires, by the roaling of
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:22457:44"/> our eyes by variety of veſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, by exquiſite practiſes to augment our bodily b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. But how much more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient were it for vs to goe about to garniſh the ſoule, wherein the true beauty is and ſuch as may by vs daily be made more beautifull? Yet we on the contrary, conſume the whole race of our life in ſpoyling the miſtreſſe, and in adorning the maiden: leauing the miſtreſſe (like a vile bond-woman) vntrimmed, beſpot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, vtterly couered with all vnſeemely ſluttiſhnes. When as God for this cauſe, exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vs from the carke of this body, and incloſed it within the bonds of nature, leaſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing occupied in needles cares,<note place="margin">Soules defiled with ſin, may bee trimmed againe.</note> wee ſhould neglect the beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying of our ſoule, whoſe beauty and braueneſſe, albeit it be brought to extreame pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, yet by our labour and diligence ſhee may be reſtored to notable gayneſſe, and
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:22457:45"/> be recouered ſo farre, that ſhee may not onely bee admired of all good men, but be deſired and loued of the king himſelfe, who is Lord of all. As the Prophet ſpeaketh to it in the Pſalmes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The king ſhall haue pleaſure in thy beauty.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſa.</hi> 45.11</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Often times experience proueth, that of thoſe women which haue beene inured to common brothelrre, if any bee ſomewhat handſome for faire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ſake ſhe hath beene vnited in matrimony to ſome good man, and hath beene drawne to honeſtie. How much rather will not God contemne ne diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſe the ſoules which haue fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len from their diuine excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy by the tyranny of the diuel, into the brothelhouſe and ſtewes of this preſent life: You ſhall find that the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets haue vſed theſe exam<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ples when they ſpake to Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, for ſhe played the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honeſt woman, and went a whoring after a ſtrange ſort,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:22457:45"/> as ſheweth the Prophet <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiel,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eze.</hi> 16.33</note> ſaying they giue gifts to all other whoores, but thou gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt gifts vnto thy louers, and the contrary is in thee from other women.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſe.</hi> 34.</note> And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine another ſaith; thou haſt ſitten vpon the way waiting for them, as a deſolate<note n="*" place="margin">C. quaile Or thou haſt ſit waiting for them in the wayes, as the Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bian in the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe, <hi>Iere.</hi> 3.2.</note> chough This people which had ſo played the harlot the Lord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed to himſelfe, for their captiuitie was not ſo much for their puniſhment, as for their amendment. For if in caſe God would haue puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and deſtroyed them withal he would not haue brought them home againe to their natiue ſoile, neither would haue cauſed them to reedifie with greater magnificency, their Citie and Temple which were ouerthrowen: the glory (ſaith he) of this laſt houſe,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Hagg.</hi> 2.10</note> ſhall be greater then the firſt. So then if God doe not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid repentance to thoſe that haue ſo manifoldly practiſed
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:22457:46"/> whooredome, he will much more willingly reclaime thy ſoule, which now firſt hath grieuouſly falne.<note place="margin">God is iealous ouer our ſoules.</note> The reaſon is, for that no carnall louer, though neuer ſo hoate, can bee ſo ielous ouer the loue of his de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ling, as God is kindled with the loue of our ſoules. Which albeit dayly it may bee gathered, yet it may be appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantly proued out of the word of God In a word, read that is ſpoken of God, in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning either of <hi>Ieremie,</hi> or of the other Prophets, how when he was deſpiſed and ſet light by of the people, yet hee returned againe to them, and thirſting after their loue, hee continually followed them And this is that, which God himſelfe declareth in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.37 <hi>Luk.</hi> 13.34.</note> where he ſaith. Hieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, Hieruſalem which killeſt the Prophets, and ſtoneſt them which are ſent to thee how often would I haue ga<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thered thy children together,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:22457:46"/> as the Hen gathereth her chic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens, and ye would not. And <hi>Paule</hi> ſaith to the Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans: For God was in Chriſt,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.19</note> and reconciled the world to himſelfe, not imputing their ſinnes vnto them, and hath committed to vs the word of reconciliation. Now then are we Ambaſſadours for Chriſt: as though god hid beſeech you through vs wee pray you in Chriſts ſtead that ye be recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled to God Let vs thinke theſe things ſpoken to vs, for not onely infidelitie, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t the polution and vncleannes of life maketh this excerable e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimitie betwixt God and men, and ſo the Apoſtle ſaith, that the wiſedome of the fleſh is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimity againſt God.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.7.</note> Go too then, let vs raze to the ground this wall of enimitie, let vs ſmooth the way to an attone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with God, that we may be loued &amp; deſired of him again</p>
                  <p>I am ſure you wonder not a little at the beauty
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:22457:47"/> of Hermione,<note place="margin">Hermio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne daugh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter to Me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nelaus &amp; Helena very beau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiful, for whom O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſtes the ſonne of Aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memnon ſlew Pyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thus the ſonne of Achilles, becauſe hee mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trothed minion.</note> and thinke the like may not be found on the whole earth. But if you wold (my friend) you may be ſo much fairer and comelier then ſhe, by how much gold exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth dirt. For if many haue in admiration the beauty of that body, and fall in loue therwith what fairenes do you thinke to be in a ſoule, if euery point therein were liuely portraited? How much more amiable, how much more wonderfull would it be? For the ſubſtance of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily beauty co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſteth in naught elſe, but in phlegme, blood, moiſture, and<note n="*" place="margin">Or me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy.</note> gall, which are maintained by the corruptible iuyces of meates? Hereby the aples of the eyes gliſter, here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the cheekes are ruddy and hereby the whole face is ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. And vnleſſe they be dayly moiſtened with ſuch iuyce, which aſcendeth out of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, incontinent the ſkin is dryed vp, the eyes waxe hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, al ruddines and beauty
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:22457:47"/> departeth from the viſage. Now if thou conſider what is hidden within that ſkin which thou iudgeſt beautifull, what is ſhut vp in the noſtrils what within the iawes and belly, thou wilt proteſt that this brauery of body, is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but a blanched ſepulchre which without appeareth faire to men, but within is full of filthynes and vnclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. Moreouer, if thou ſee on a ragged cloath, the phlegme and ſpittle that proceedeth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the body, thou loatheſt it, and wilt not touch it with the tip of the finger, looking aſkew theron: &amp; how then canſt thou loue and deſire the cel and ſeat of phlegme? But thy beauty was not ſuch. For by how much heauen is more beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full than the earth, by ſo much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>id the trimnes of thy ſoule <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>urmount the beauty of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aireſt body. And notwiſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing none at any time hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eene a ſoule departed from the
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:22457:48"/> body, yet ſome other time I wil attempt to delare the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines of it, by the powers ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. At this time let it ſuffice to rehearſe the words of the Lord, which ſay, they are as the Angels of God in heauen. Againe,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat</hi> 22.30 <hi>Mar</hi> 12.25</note> in that of bodies there is ſo great a difference, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene thoſe that are thin, and thoſe that are thicke and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy (as for example heauen paſſeth the earth, fire water, the ſtars ſtones the rainebowe all terreſtriall flowers:) wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> would wee ſay, if it might ſo chance that with corporal eies, we might behold y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gaineſſe of the ſoule? Wouldeſt thou not ſcoffe at all externall beauty and brauery, in conſideration of that internall ſubſtance? I pray thee then let vs not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temn ſo great a felicity, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard lightly ſo great a treaſure that is in vs, eſpecially ſith a returne is not hard and with no great labour may all the beauty of our ſoule be renued
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:22457:48"/> For as ſoone as thou ſhalt i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magine the things to come, and thou ſhalt be inamored with them, ſtraightway the ſoule retireth to her former brauenes. So it is written;<note place="margin">2. <hi>Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi> 4.17</note> For our light affliction, which is but for a moment, cauſeth vnto vs a farre more excellent.<note place="margin">18.</note> an an eternall weight of glory. While we looke not on the things which are ſeene, but on the things which are not ſeene, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> things which are ſeene are corporal but the things which are not ſeene are eternall. Now if <hi>Paule</hi> call tribula<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons light and eaſie, for that we looke not on the things which are ſeene, but on the things which are not ſaue: how much more eaſie ſhall it be for thee to ſhake of the foule burden of vncleannes? Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther now doe I exhort thee to thoſe labours and dangers<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or to thoſe daily deaths, which the Apoſtles ſuffered, or to thoſe perſecutions or ſtripes
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:22457:49"/> or bands, or impriſonments, or the contempt of all worldly riches, or famine. or nakednes, or many watchings, or perils of iourneying, or ſhipwrackes on ſea, or dangers of robbers, or dangers of thine own nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or dangers of falſe bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, for all thoſe afflictions the Apoſtles indured: nothing of all theſe I require of thee, but this I deſire alone, that ſeruitude being forſaken, thou returne to thy former liberty, conſidering both the plague which followeth riot, and the glory which is laid vp for ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues. It is no maruell if thoſe which beleeue there ſhall be no reſurrection, neglect their life, feare nothing the iudgement to come, and are nothing pric<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked in heart: but wee which looke more certainely on future then preſent things, ought we to liue ſo miſerably, and wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chedly, that wee not onely ſhould not feare at the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of the iudgement to
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:22457:49"/> come, but vtterly contemne it?</p>
                  <p>A part it is of extreame madnes and no miſchiefe is comparable, that beleeuing we be like the vnbeleeuing. Yea amongſt them not a few haue beene found, who haue flouriſhed in this life, in the vertues of the mind, and what ſhall be our excuſe, what our ſolace, if in the day of doome thoſe ſhall be brought forth for examples againſt vs? Some that exerciſe marchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe we ſee haue ſuffered ſhip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wracke, and the loſſe of all their goods: yet for this they haue not beene diſmayed, but againe haue applyed the ſame way and trafficke. Theſe did <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eeſe their ſubſtance not by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oth but by violence of winds But we which know afore vndoubtedly, that if we our ſelues wil we may incur nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhipwrack nor damage of ſoule; ſhuld we not take in hand againe our former exerciſes, &amp; renue our buſines by negly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:22457:50"/> ouerſlipped? Neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe we lie retchleſly, and fold our idle hands on our breaſt, after the manner of ſluggards and would God our hands were idle, and did not worke our owne decay, Which if they doe it hath great affinitie with moſt manifeſt outrage, as if (for example) a champion lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing his aduerſary, ſhould turne his hands on his owne head, and buffet himſelfe. The diuell hath put vs to flight, and hath daſhed vs in ſunder, we haue need then to riſe and to reſiſt him. When thou art once caſt downe, if thou be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling not onely to lie ſtill, but to throw downe thy ſelfe head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long this is to aſſent to thine enemie, and to take in defence his part.</p>
                  <p>Bleſſed <hi>Dauid</hi> fell after rhe ſame ſort, thou diddeſt, neither ſo alone, but in more grieuous wiſe, for he combined murder, with adultery: and what did he then? Did he lie ſo? Did he
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:22457:50"/> not riſe and reſiſt the enemy, and ſo ouercame him, that his good deeds profited his poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity ween he was gone? For when <hi>Salomon</hi> had commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that hainous crime, and was deemed worthy of a thou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſand deaths, yet for <hi>Dauids</hi> ſake the Lord ſaid he would beſtow the kingdome on him longer. Theſe be the words; I will ſurely rent the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome from thee,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Ki.</hi> 11.11</note> and will giue it to thy ſeruant. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding in thy daies I will not doe it,<note place="margin">12.</note> becauſe of <hi>Dauid</hi> thy father,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Ki.</hi> 19.34</note> but I will rent it out of the hand of thy ſonne. <hi>Hezechiah</hi> when he was much indangered, (albeit he were a iuſt man himſelfe,) yet for bleſſed <hi>Dauid</hi> the Lord promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to helpe him,<note n="*" place="margin">Or, I will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend this citie to ſaue it for mine own ſake, and for Dauid my ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantes ſake.</note> I will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend this Citie for mine owne ſake, and for <hi>Dauid</hi> my ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants ſake, I will ſaue it. See what was the ſtrength of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance ſee what power con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion had. But if he had
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:22457:51"/> thus thought, (which thou now thinkeſt.) and had ſaid it is impoſſible that the Lord ſhould now be merciful to me, he hath greatly honoured me, and hath endued me with the gift of prophecy, he hath exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted me to a kingdome, he hath deliuered me from manifold dangers, how then can I promerite clemencie at the hands of God, foraſmuch as I haue thus fallen? If <hi>Dauid</hi> had thus thought, he had lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> not only y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> went afore but that that followed alſo. For not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the wounds of the body if they be neglected bring death; but the wounds of the ſoule ſemblably. Are we ſo ſottiſh to put a plaiſter to a bodily wound, and neuer attempt to cure the ſoule? Many wounds of our body may not be cured, yet we diſpaire not, and though y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Chirurgions ſay y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wound is vncu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>able, yet we earneſtly and vrgently beſeech them, that they would mittigate ſome
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:22457:51"/> what the paine. But in the wounds of the ſoule; which are not vnſanable, (for the ſoule is not tyed to neceſſity neither abideth any paſſion) we are remiſſe, we are paſt hope, we are pricked with no care When there is no hope our griefe of body may be healed, yet we withdraw no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing from our care: but here when no occaſion is of deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, without vſing any la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, we omit all care. So you perceiue, how that more ardently we loue our body then our ſoule, knowing not, that if we regard not our ſoule we cannot ſaue our body. For the ſoule was not ordained for the body, but the body for the ſoule: and he that eſteemeth not the higher but poliſheth the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour, marreth both. But he that obſerueth an order, and garniſheth the firſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitte hee doe not paſſe for the ſecond, by the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation neuertheleſſe of the
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:22457:52" rendition="simple:additions"/> firſt the ſeeond ſhall be ſaued. The which is builded on the plot of Chriſt his words, Feare ye not them which kill th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> body,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.28</note> but are not able to kill the ſoule; but rather feare him, which is able to deſtroy both body and ſoule in Hell.</p>
                  <p>Thinke you we haue done enough, and ſatiſfied you in this thing, that no infirmity of the ſoule is vncureable? Or elſe is it needfull wee ſhould vſe other reaſons, and confirme it yet further? For although a thouſand times thou diſpaire of thy ſelfe, wee will neuer diſpaire of thee. Neither doe we this that wee miſlike in other, howbeit there be ods, whether one diſpaire of himſelfe, or another of him. To diſpaire of another is par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donable but to diſpaire of him ſelfe is not: becauſe he is not maſter of anothers mind, this ruleth his owne purpoſe Wherefore we hope there is a returne for you to the ſtate of
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:22457:52"/> your former life, and to the vertues of the minde, which we know are in you. Beſides theſe things this we adde.</p>
                  <p>The Nineuits heard the Prophet ſaying definitely,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Jon.</hi> 2.4.</note> yet forty dayes, and Nineueh ſhal be ouerthrown, notwitſtanding they were not diſcouraged No not when they were not certaine, that the Lord would not bring to paſſe his words, and when (in mans iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) there was no hope of forgiueneſſe. And as ſoone as that abrupt ſaying was end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, they determined repentance ſaying who can tell if God will turne and repent,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſe.</hi> 9. 10.</note> and turne away his fierce wrath that we periſh not. And God ſaw their workes that they turned from their euill waies: and God repented of the euill that he had ſaid he would doe vnto them and he did it not. If Barbarians and ignorant folke could vnderſtand ſo much of the mercy of God,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:22457:53"/> doth it not much more behoue vs to do ſo. who are inſtructed in the word of God, and know this example was before our time and that many more like are contained in Gods booke, either in words,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iſai.</hi> 55.8.</note> or in acts? For my thoughts are not your thoughts, neither are your wayes my wayes, ſaith the Lord.<note place="margin">9.</note> For as the heauens are higher then the earth, ſo are my wayes higher the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your wayes, and my thoughts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue your thoughts</p>
                  <p>Farthermore if we receiue our ſeruants, who haue offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vs, when they promiſe they will amend, and account of them as before, nay many times credit them more after reconcilement; will not God much rarher deale thus with vs? If he had made vs to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh vs, thou mighteſt well de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire, and doubt of thy ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation: but if for his goodnes, onely he made vs to enioy his euer-during bliſſe and rewards
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:22457:53"/> and doth al things from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the world till this day, to this end and purpoſe, that he may ſaue vs: what mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter of deſpairing what matter of miſdoubting is there left?</p>
                  <p>We haue offended him (ſay you) more than euer any man. For this cauſe ſhouldeſt thou more ſpeedily and earneſtly make ſatiſfaction and be ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull for thine offence, and abandon thoſe deedes with which God is offended. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth a grieuous iniury offende any body ſo much, as to continue in it, when there is time and opportun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tie of ſatisfaction. To ſinne is hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane, but to perſeuer in ſinne, is diabolicall. To conclude,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Hier.</hi> 3.7. Or, and I ſaid, when ſhe had done all this, turne thou vnto me, but ſhe retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned not.</note> behold how God by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet miſtiketh this more then that: And I haue ſaid (ſaith he) after that ſhe hath in all this gone a whooring be thou turned to me, and ſhe is not turned. And other-where, when he had rebuked the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>greſſions
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:22457:54"/> of the people, by his Prophet, and they had promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed amendment, hee ſheweth how louingly he receiueth the conuerſion of ſinners, who wil grant their heart may be ſo in them, that they may feare me, and keepe my commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments all the daies of their life, that it may be well with them, and rheir children for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uermore? Moſes likewiſe, when he would teach the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, what God requireth of men,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Deu.</hi> 10.12</note> ſaith thus: And now, Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, what doth the Lord thy God require of thee, but to feare the Lord thy God, to walke in all his wayes, and to loue him, and to ſerue thy Lord thy God with all thy heart and with all thy ſoule.</p>
                  <p>God then, who is deſirous that himſelf be beloued of vs, and for this doth all things, not ſparing his onely begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten for our ſaluation, and the loue he bare towards vs, wold faine (after what fort ſoeuer,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:22457:54"/> if I may ſo ſpeake) we ſhould be reconciled to him; and how can it be, that he ſhould not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue and loue vs being peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents conuerted vnto him, and that as cheerefully as he doth his children? For in what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect doe you thinke, ſpake hee by the Prophet, ſaying<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Tell thou thine iniquities firſt, that thou maiſt be iuſtified? Was it not for that he coueted to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke vs to his loue,<note place="margin">Amantium irae amoris redinte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratio eſt.</note> and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der affection? He that loueth his friend, if perchance he ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer many iniuries at his hands, his loue is not for that cooled towards his beloued, if in caſe he will let the wrongs to be opened and diſcouered, and certes he that is iniured, doth deſire this for no other cauſe, but that their renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of loue may be of more force and validity. Now, if the confeſſion of ſinnes mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treth ſo much to attonement, how much greater may be our hope of reconciliation, if by
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:22457:55"/> workes of repenance we blot out the offences we haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted? For if God prohibited the fallen to returne to the right way, either none, or very few ſhould enter the kingdom of heauen. Yea, the cheefe Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarchs whom we haue in admiration, after backeſlides in ſinnes, they haue beene re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored. For they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were earneſt in euill, being turned to good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes vſe the ſame forwardnes, knowing that their debt is great. In the Goſpell this is taught of the Lord, when he ſaid to <hi>Simon</hi> of a certaine wo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>man Seeſt thou this woman I entred into thine houſe and thou gaueſt me no water to my feet, but ſhe hath waſhed my feet with teares,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luke.</hi> 7.44</note> and wiped them with the haires of her head. Thou gaueſt me no kiſſe, but ſhe ſince y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time I came in,<note place="margin">45.</note> hath not ceaſed to kiſſe my feete, My head with oile thou didſt not annoint:<note place="margin">46.</note> but ſhe hath annoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted my feete with oyntment.
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:22457:55"/> Wherefore I ſay vnto thee,<note place="margin">47.</note> many ſins are forgiuen her, for ſhe loued much. To whom a little is forgiuen, he doth loue a little.<note place="margin">48.</note> And he ſaid vnto her thy ſins are forgiuen thee. For which cauſe the diuell know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that they which haue ſold themſelues to worke iniquity, if they reuolt, are diligent and ſerious and as in their tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions they were haſtie, ſo in their amendment they are heedefull, (becauſe now they know what they haue done,) he feareth and ſhaketh leaſt any of them ſhould make the onſet to repentance. For if they once begin, they may not be withſtood, but kindled with the heat of repentance, as it were with fire, they make their ſoules purer than fined gold, &amp; by the remembrance of their former miſdeeds, and as it were by the blowing wind of their conſcience, hauing hope their pilot, they ariue in the hauen of health. And bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:22457:56"/> of the horrours paſt, the circumſpecter they are in their iourney; ſo that in this wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nigh they may ſeeme to paſſe thoſe that neuer faultered, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe experience maketh them more chary.<note place="margin">Experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia ſtulto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</note> For (I know not how) we loue more entirely the things we had and haue loſt, then the things we haue not and deſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e to get.</p>
                  <p>Then a hard thing it is, (as I ſaid) to make a begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in this lyeth all the diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty, to prepare the way to repentance. For ſtraight way at the entrance the enemy blow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth out threats &amp; menacings, and in his rage driueth vs backe, when we would goe forth. The ſmokie puffes, and cloude of whoſe terrours, if thou contemne, when the way is entred, thou ſhalt ſee thy ſelf corroborated, and obtaining the conqueſt thou wilt reioyce thine enemy menaced thee and thou ſhalt perceiue the reſt of this combate eaſie. Go too, go
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:22457:56"/> too, in the name of God, now let vs enter the path of life, let vs returne to the heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly city, ſeeing we are appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and inrolled citizens. The gates of this Citie deſpaire ſhutteth againſt vs, hope and confidence will open them ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; the which if we caſt behind vs we incurre the crime, not of ſloath alone, but of arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancy For ſathan was made as he is by no other meanes but for that after his ſinne firſt he deſpaired and n xt fell from deſpaire into hautines and pride. So likewiſe the ſoule if it once begin to deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire of ſaluation, it vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandeth not into what miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefes it runneth, fearing not to ſpeake or doe whatſoeuer may ſtop ſaluation. Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly we ſee in thoſe that are mad when once they haue loſt their wit, they feare naught any longer, they bluſh at nothing, but licentiouſly they dare ſpeake and doe euery thing.
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:22457:57"/> If they fall into the fire, they auoid it not, if they be going into a headlong place, they pull not back their foote. After the ſame manner they that are in deſpaire commit intollerable actes, they range in all the waies of wickednes, ſhame is no let, feare hindreth nothing, the things preſent do not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frain them, the things to come do not terrifie, death only it is that they cannot eſcape.</p>
                  <p>Wherefore I humbly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt thee, before the poiſon of this ſin more infect thee, ariſe and awake at the laſt, and lay aſide this deuelliſh drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. If on the ſudden thou canſt not gather thy wits to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, yet doe it leiſurely, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though (in my opinion) it be the eaſier way at once to break off all the ſtaies of this euill, to ſheere it in ſunder fully, and to begin repentance anew But if this be difficile vnto thee, as thou wilt and art a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, begin a better conuerſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:22457:57"/> and couet eternall life. Runne therefore I pray and beſeech you deare friend, (I beſeech you for thoſe good deeds you haue done hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, I pray you for the liberty that firſt you had) let me ſee you clime vp to the top of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, as truely a repentant as you were before. Yeeld to me thy friend, yeeld to all them that are offended through thee, and fall becauſe of thy fall, yeeld to all them that are in deſpaire becauſe of thy deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire, that they may not ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe they cannot tread the true way, vnleſſe they ſee thee returne. Regard (I deſire you) the penſiueneſſe of the whole congregation of the faithfull brethren, the great ioy and triumphing of the faithleſſe, the vſuall by words of ſlouthfull youthes, regard wbat authority thou art to many to wallow in the mire of riot. And if ſo be that you returne into the way of your
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:22457:58"/> former vertues, all theſe things will be turned into the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Our ſhame and confuſion ſhall light on them, we ſhall be ioyfull and glad. For we will blaze abrode throughout the world, that thou art a ſubduer of luſt, a ſubduer of vncleane and fooliſh voluptie and riot, and we will brute farre and wide thy glorious triumph. That victory is the greater that is gotten after a fall, and that is reſtored after flight. And you ſhall not onely be rewarded, for your owne la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and reformation, but ſhall receiue a meede for the ſafety of them, who leuelling their life to thy conuerſation haue (without diſpaire) retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned themſelues to repentance. Neither any hereafter hauing fallen howſoeuer, will not be greedy by and by to riſe, and incontinently to be reſtored Deſpiſe not (if you loue me) theſe great profits, neither bring our ſoules with ſorrow
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:22457:58"/> to the graue: but vouchſafe vs ſome reſt, and chaſe away the cloud of heauines, which for thy ſake hath ouercouered vs; for loe letting paſſe our owne euils, we bewaile thy fall. But if you would a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle looke vpward, and be in loue with celeſtiall things, we ſhould be eaſed of this lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. and we might be cauſed to conſider our owne offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
                  <p>That men may by repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance repaire their priſtine gaineſſe yea ſomtimes be made more excellent than before they were, hetherto we haue confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med out of the word of God. And to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude this point, this is the cauſe why that harlots and Publicans inherit the kingdome of heauen, and that many that were laſt, ſhall be firſt, Henceforth I will adde the things that haue beene done in our age, of which thou<note n="*" place="margin">G. F. C. of which my ſelfe may bee a witnes.</note> thy ſelfe art a witnes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">G. F. C. I know.</note>You know that yong man
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:22457:59"/> the ſonne of <hi>Vrbanus,</hi> the chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt of that prouince whoſe parents died in his minority, but left him very wealthy in houſhold ſtuffe, gold, ſiluer and poſſeſſions. That youth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temning at the firſt all pompe, and pride, (which that age and ritches for the moſt part follow) he left the ſchooles of humane artes, and betooke himſelfe to a baſe life in which putting on courſe and homely arayment, he departed to the mountaines and deſart places. Where being exerciſed in the temperancy of true philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy, he not onely matched (which is but ſeldome ſeene in thoſe yeeres,) but paſſed too, great and wonderfull men in the vertue of abſtinency; yea when afterward he was bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed he paſſingly increaſed in vertues At which thing all reioyced, &amp; prayſed the Lord, that borne to ſo great wealth, &amp; deſcended of ſuch a family, euen in the Aprill of his daies
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:22457:59"/> he troad vnder foote at once all vanity of this momentary life, and had an hungry deſire of eternall ioy.</p>
                  <p>Liuing after this ſort, and in this admiration, among all, certaine of his kindred (but naughty perſons) at the firſt came to ſee him, and after by continuance of lewd talke,<note place="margin">Euill ſpee<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ches cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt good manners.</note> drew him againe to that he hated and loathed, ſo that all philoſophy (which he ſtudied) being layed apart, he came from the hilles to the market place. Then carried on a pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frey through the midſt of the citie, and guarded with foote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, he vauntingly began to wander vp and downe the ſtreetes. Inſomuch that the raines of chaſtity were alſo let looſe, becauſe it hath no fellowſhippe with dainties and ryot. After this he was ſnarled in the baite of filthy loue, and led into captiuitie by euery luſt, which cauſed all men
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:22457:60"/> to deſpaire of his ſaluation. For ſwarmes of paraſites en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uironed this hope loſt yonker the adulterous rabble com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed him in. And what hope would a man thinke to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining? Thoſe alſo which were giuen very much to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending, found fault with this likewiſe, that in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gining he entred a courſe, he could not continue in, and had aſpired to that was aboue his reach, forſaking the ſtudy of learning wherein he might haue profited.</p>
                  <p>When theſe and ſuch like things as touching his life be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing rumored abroad, were knowne to all, and we alſo were aſhamed of his doing; certaine holy men, expert in this kind of hunting, and who had found out by long vſe and experience, that naught was to be deſpaired, putting on the armour of hope, they began to watch him more narrowly. And if it fortuned he were in
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:22457:60"/> the ſtreet, they approached neere and courteouſly ſaluted him; but he on horſe-backe ſcarce greeted them againe, or thought them worthy an anſwere, when they went by his ſide; ſuch was his pride and wickednes. But thoſe mercifull men, accounting none of theſe an iniury, reſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted only that they had inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that they m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ght (if it were poſſible by any meanes) deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the lambe out of the teeth of wolues; which by patience was in fine achiued. For weigh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing they did this often, and prying into his owne life with the inward eyes of his mind, he bluſhed ſomewhat at their boldneſſe and tendring, and when he marked they came a far off, he would diſmount from his horſe, and bowing his head towards the earth, he harkened diligently to their ſpeeches, and in proceſſe of time he reuerenced them more. And ſo reuolting by peece-meale,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:22457:61"/> through the grace of God, and their meeke coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, and rid from all the nets of death wherin he was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangled, he went againe to the wildernes, to the mountaines, and to the wonted exerciſes of philoſophie, and after was of ſuch humilitie, that his lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter doings exceeded his won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull beginning. He learned by proofe the occaſion of his fall, and the allurement of all his error. That alſo he did, which (doubtleſſe) was agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to Chriſts commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the Goſpell;<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.21</note> Selling all he had, and diſtributing it on the poore, to the end he might remooue his treaſure from the earth to heauen, and his heart might bee there, where his treaſure was. But becauſe as yet hee had ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what left on earth, his heart returned to the earth, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king an eſtimate of all his goodes. (for he cared nothing for them) he beſtowed much
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:22457:61"/> on the needy, that ſo freeing himſelfe from care of mind, he might take away all occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſtumbling. And thus walking in the way to heauen by amendment he is come to each accomplement of vertue: ſo you ſee, how this yong man fell quickly, and aroſe ſpeedily.</p>
                  <p>Another alſo after many la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours he had ſuſtained in the wildernes, hauing onely the company of one in his life and manſion place, continued an Angelicall life, from his yong age, to his very old daies.<note n="*" place="margin">Good Lord, how much difference is there betweene the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Maſſe-mongring Moonkes now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Monks which were in Chriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes dayes? Thoſe were continent, and ſequeſtred (although they ſhould haue had a care of the ſaluation of their brethren al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo) themſelues from the vulgar ſort of men to the end they might giue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to contemplation and meditation, (for this was the cauſe why Baſill the great went to Pontus, and inuited his friend Gregory the Diuine to him,) theſe are lecherous and luſtfull, coueting that ſort of life for idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes alone, and belly cheere. Thoſe a ſoone as they perceiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their vnclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes (this fellow heere alleaged is a wit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes) fel to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance without ſtay: theſe through ſenſuality commit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ting groſſe &amp; carnall ſins, neuer truely repent for it, and yet beare men in hand they are the holieſt perſons vnder the Sunne. Of whom it was ſaid rightly though in a rithme,
<q>
                           <l>O monachi, veſtri ſtomachi, ſunt amphora Bacchi!</l>
                           <l>Vos eſtis, Deus eſt teſtis, turpiſſima peſtis.</l>
                        </q> Let none then of the ignorant ſort ſuppoſe that this example maketh ought for the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightnes of Moonkes now a daies.</note> But (I know not how)
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:22457:62"/> drowſily yeelding to the ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion and firſt battery of the diuell, he fell into the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of a woman, when as hee neuer ſaw any, ſithence he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a Moonke. Firſt, then he deſired his fellow with whom he liued, to bring him wine, and fleſh to feed on, who making no haſt, he threatned him, that he would goe downe into the city. Which he ſaid not that he might eat fleſh, but that he might find opportunity to ſatiſfie his luſt. His compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on marueiling at this and fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring leaſt he ſhould doe him more harme, if he ſhould deny
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:22457:62"/> his requeſt, gaue that he aſked, and fulfilled his will. When he ſaw no way to guile, open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſhameleſly, he reuealeth his deſire, and confeſſeth he will goe downe to the Citie. The other by much perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion not able to retaine him, let him goe and followed him a far off, to ſe what he would doe and whither he would go. And when a great way behind he ſaw him entring a brothel-houſe, and to haue cooled his luſt with the company of a ſtrumpet, tarrying at the dore ſtraightway when he came forth, he exhorted him to repen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tance, he imbraced him, and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uingly kiſſed him, and rebuked him not for his fal, but deſired him that now his luſt being cooled, he would returne to his old habitation, and to the ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary wildernes. But he mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in him ſuch meekeneſſe and gentlenes, was aſhamed, and ſtroken thorow with the force of his words and deeds,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:22457:63"/> and condemning himſelfe for his miſdemeaner, goeth with his fellow (which was ſo good and humble) into the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine. Whither when they came he entreated of him, that when he was ſhut vp cloſely in his cell, and heremitage, he would<note n="*" place="margin">G.F.C. dayly.</note> euery ſecond day bring him bread and water, If any ſhould ſeeke him, he willed him to ſay, that he was<note n="*" place="margin">G.F.C. a ſleepe</note> dead. Which things obtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, he ſhut vp himſelfe, and thereabode, clenſing the foul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his ſinne, with faſting, prayers, and weeping.</p>
                  <p>Few daies paſſed ouer, when a drowth (becauſe of the want of raine) had hurte the country neere about him, and all the inhabitants of that land lamented much. But one of them was warned in a dreame to goe to that man in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſed in a cell, that he might pray, and that by no other way raine might be procured, but by his prayers, So depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:22457:63"/> with ſome other taken to him, he found this Monkes complice alone, and demaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded where he was, whom the viſion admoniſhed him to ſeek. When he heard he was dead, he deemed his viſion falſe, and they returned all to prayer, but the ſame viſion tolde him againe the ſame things. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at earneſtly entreating him, that before had deceiued them, they requeſted him to ſhew them the man, affirming that by the authority of ſo maruei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous a viſion, they were ſent to him being aliue, not dead. Seeing it was the wil of God he brings them to that godly man, and the wall being bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken downe, (becauſe he had ſhut the doore,) they enter in and fall before his feete, deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring him (when the truth of the matter was decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red) to releaſe the famine by interceſſion. Firſt, his excuſe was, that hee could not demerite ſo great a thing.
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:22457:64"/> at which words, he burſt forth into weeping for the offence he had committed, as if he had ſeene it freſh before his eies. At length for the importuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the requeſters, (for as much as he perceiued God would haue it ſo,) he gaue him ſelfe to ſupplication, and out of hand there followed, great ſtore of raine, wherwith both the earth and men were refreſhed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Read Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebius hiſt eccl, lib. 3. cap. 23.</note>What ſhould I ſpeake of him which firſt was the deſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciple of <hi>Iohn</hi> the<note n="*" place="margin">G.F.C. ſonne of Zebidaeus</note> Apoſtle, but after practiſed robbing for a long time? Neuertheleſſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward the Apoſtle got hold on him, as he came out from the robbers den, and brought him again (as you will know) to his former life, ſo that his beginning was not to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred with his end. I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber when you read this ſtory you admired the incredible meekenes of this Apoſtle, and among other tokens of his
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:22457:64"/> ſincere loue towards him, which he ſhewed, this you ſaid you moſt wondered at that he kiſſed the hand of the young man beſmeared with bloud, and ſo with imbracing reclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med him to euerlaſting life, when as by all likelihood he was neare to the brinke of death.</p>
                  <p>Saint <hi>Paule</hi> alſo not onely loued and embraced <hi>Oneſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> conuerted, who was an vnprofitable ſeruant, and fugi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue theefe, but maketh petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to his maſter, that he ſhuld eſteeme him as himſelfe, and that becauſe he recanted.<note place="margin">Philem. from the 10. verſe to the 18.</note> Theſe be the Apoſtles words I beſeech thee for my ſonne <hi>Oneſimus,</hi> whom I haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten in my bonds. Which in time paſt was to thee vnprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, but now profitable both to thee and to me, whom I haue ſent againe, thou therfore receiue him, that is mine owne bowels. Whom I wold haue retained with me, that in thy
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:22457:65"/> ſtead he might haue miniſtred vnto me in the bonds of the Goſpell. But without thy mind, would I doe nothing that thy benefite ſhould be as it were, of neceſſity, but wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly. It may be that he ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore departed for a ſeaſon, that thou ſhouldeſt receiue him for euer, not now as a ſeruant, but aboue a ſeruaunt, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as a brother beloued, ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to me, how much more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto thee, both in the fleſh, and in the Lord? If therefore thou account our things com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, receiue him, as my ſelfe.</p>
                  <p>The ſame Apoſtle writeth to the Corinthians, touching them that haue ſinned, in this wiſe,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.22.</note> leaſt when I come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, I ſhall bewaile many of them which haue ſinned al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, and haue not repented of the vncleannes,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.2</note> and forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and wantonnes which they haue committed And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, I told you before, and tell you before, if I come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:22457:65"/> I will not ſpare. You ſee then whom the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle bewayleth, and whom he will not ſpare, not thoſe which haue ſinned, but thoſe which haue not repented, and not onely not repented, but once or twiſe admoniſhed of their faults haue refuſed to obey. For in that he ſaith, I told you before, and tell you before, as though I had beene preſent the ſecond time, ſo write I now being abſent, he ſignifieth thus much, that being warned they contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned counſell.</p>
                  <p>For which cauſe, I feare me, the ſame will fall out to vs, and although the ſame <hi>Paule,</hi> who threatned the Corinthians, bee not at our elbowes, yet Chriſt is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, who ſpake by him, and if wee perſeuer in hardneſſe of heart, he will ſay to vs, I will not ſpare you, not onely in the time preſent, but not in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time to come neither,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:22457:66"/> Wherefore let vs preuent his face by confeſſion,<note place="margin">We will acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge our ſins, and in confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend not to com: mit them againe, aſſuring our ſelues of remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. <hi>Ecclus.</hi> 21.1 <hi>Pro.</hi> 18.17 Or, he that is firſt in his cauſe is iuſt.</note> and let vs power out our hearts in his ſight, * Haſt thou ſinned? Saith the Scripture, doe ſo no more, pray for thy fore-ſins that they may be forgiuen thee, And againe, * The iuſt is an accuſer of himſelfe in the beginning of his ſpeech. Let vs not then looke till our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſary accuſe vs, but let vs preuent him by confeſſion, and ſo make the iudge more fauourable towards vs.</p>
                  <p>And ſurely this I aſſured<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly know, thou confeſſeſt thy tranſgreſſions, and mourneſt for thy ſelfe, but this I doe not alonely require of thee; for I would haue the amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the things to come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe, of the confeſſion of the things paſt, and ſo I would haue it done, that whileſt thou doeſt it be thou aſcertained of forgi eneſſe. For euery one that doth ought, vnleſſe he know the thing he hath in
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:22457:66"/> hand will profit him goeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it, either careleſly, or not ſeriouſly. For example he that ſoweth ſeed, vnles he be ſure and certaine there will be raine, that the earth will ſend forth the blade, and that the fruit will ripen, he will neuer reape. And as none would faine ſpend labour in waſt, nor beſtow diligence in that which ſhall not be beneficiall vnto him; ſo he that ſoweth ſorrow, teares and confeſſion which is without hope vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable, cannot ceaſe from ſinne, being holden faſt by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credulity. But as the huſband man which hath no hope to reape fruit careth not to driue off the birds from his corne, or beaſts, or any other nociue things, right ſo he that ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth confeſſion with teares, and hopeth not it will be gainefull, putteth and driueth nothing from his heart, which may hurt repentance. Repentance is hurted, if it be enwrapped,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:22457:67"/> in ſuch euils as hee was firſt; When one buildeth and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther breaketh downe,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ecclus.</hi> 34, 24.</note> what profit haue they then (ſaith the ſcripture) but labour? And he that is purged from the tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of a corſe, and againe toucheth the dead, what auai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth waſhing? So he that faſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth to decline ſinnes, and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth backe againe to them, who will heare his prayers?<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ecclus.</hi> 26, 29.</note> And againe it is ſaid, when one de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parteth from righteouſneſſe to ſinne, the Lord appoynteth ſuch to the ſword. And as a dog is odious that licketh vp his vomite againe,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Prou.</hi> 26.11.</note> ſo is a fool<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he returneth to his tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions.</p>
                  <p>So then this ſufficeth not, to accuſe thy ſelfe by declaring thy ſinnes, but doe it with that zeale, that hope of iuſtification may proceede of repentaunce, and ſo you may bridle your ſoule to commit neuer the thinges againe, of which you haue made confeſſion. One for
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:22457:67"/> to giue cenſure againſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, is common to the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and faithleſſe. Many ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors on ſtage which repreſent vnchaſt queanes &amp; whormon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers call themſelues ſinners and naughty folke, but not with purpoſe to amend, and therefore in very deede it is no confeſſion. For they ſpeake it not for griefe of heart, nor with bitterneſſe of teares, nor with hatred of the things they confeſſe, as if they would no more eyther heare or doe the like, but the words be all the matter, which they blab out with their lips, not touched or pinched in minde, but after a ſort hunting for praiſe, throgh the elegancie and trimneſſe of ſpeech, which they vſe to theyr auditors. Neither are ſinnes ſo greeuous when they are co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorably declared, as whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> indeed they are committed. Againe ſome are ſo benummed with ouer-great deſpaire, and are ſo deuoyde of ſence, that making
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:22457:68"/> like account of good &amp; illreport, with great impudency they diſcloſe their ſinnes, as though they were another bodies. But I would haue thee to do nothing ſo, neither for deſpaire to come to confeſſion but with good and ſure hope of forgiuenes, the very roote of deſpaire being cut off. Now the root of deſpaire is ſloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes, and not the root onely but the nurſe too.<note n="*" place="margin">A man is cauſed to thinke that any good thing is hard, and not poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to be obtained by him or any other through too great baſhful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: which when it ruleth in ones affection, he thinketh it may be eaſed by no good thing. And becauſe ſloathful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes is a certaine deiectiue penſiuenes of the ſpirit, it commeth to paſſe, that deſpaire ariſeth of ſloath. <hi>Thom. Aquin. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>ſ. p. q.</hi> 20. <hi>de deſper.</hi>
                     </note> For as a garment breedeth mothes, and nouriſheth them alſo, ſo ſloath doth not alone beget deſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion but nouriſheth and foſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth it. Inſomuch that they wax and grow togither, the one being cut off, the other (without queſtion) maneth and decreaſeth, Wherefore ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:22457:68"/> this link of ſinnes, and breake their yoake. By the yoake of thy ſoule, I meane vice, whereto as it were a yoake, the life of man is tyed. for when the thought of man is not right, the axle-tree of life is carried headlong,</p>
                  <p>Harken yet what more we will ſay. Often times it fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth out that a man amendeth many and great ſinnes by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, yet he committeth faults after the good he hath wrought. And this is it, which layeth chiefely deſpaire on the ſoule, becauſe ſhe ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to pull downe that ſhee builded, and vainely to haue ſpent all her trauell, this cogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation (I ſay) depriueth the ſoule of hope and confidence. Contrariwiſe we muſt thinke what way this bad &amp; hurtful thought may be expelled, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that vnleſſe the good we doe, and the amendment gotten by repentance prohibited, and were (as it were) a contrary
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:22457:69"/> weight to our ſinnes, there were no ſtay, but that wee ſhould be carried downeward into the depth of miſchiefe. And as a ſtrong habergion ſuffereth not a keine and poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned dart to pierce the intrals of the body, but in ſome part ſtoppeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> force therof: ſo is it certain that he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> carieth hence many good thinges and many bad, ſhall find ſome eaſe in his puniſhment: and he that ſhall depart without any goodneſſe, and with great ſtore of euill, what ſhould I ſpeake of his puniſhment? For there (queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onleſſe) good and bad workes ſhall be rewarded, and each (as it were) ſhall be ballanced, and the part that ſinketh, ſhal draw with it the worker.<note place="margin">Rewardes in the life to come of workes both good and bad.</note> If the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of euils ſhal ouer-poyſe, it will pull the worker to hell; but if the good works ſhall be greater, they will reſiſt and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugne againſt the euils, and will bring their worker to the place of the liuing, euen from
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:22457:69"/> the gates of hell, This is not phantaſtically imagined of my braine, the diuine Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures diſaſſent not from it; for this the word of God ſpeaketh. Thou<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. <hi>62, 12.</hi> Mat. <hi>16.27.</hi> Differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces of ioyes &amp; plagues in the life to come. Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uin. Iuſtitu. lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>25.</hi> ſect. <hi>10.</hi> Bulling, in Comment. &amp; Eraſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mus in Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raphraſ. in <hi>41,</hi> verſ. cap. <hi>15. 1</hi> Cor.</note> rewardeſt euery one according to his worke. For not in hell onely but in the kingdome of God, there ſhall be many differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Iohn.</hi> 14.2</note> In my fathers houſe (ſaith he) are many dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing places. And againe,<note n="*" place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.41.</note> There is another glory of the Sunne, and another glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Moone. What is more wonderfull, then that he ſheweth how exactly the meaſure of our deedes ſhall be weighed? One ſtarre (ſaith he) differeth from another ſtarre in glory, that by it he might ſhew that amongſt all and euery one that ſhall be in that kingdome, there willbe a difference. Therefore ſith wee know all this, let vs not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw our ſelus fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> goodworks neither yeeld to ſloth &amp; ſluggar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:22457:70"/> the preſence of deſpaire. And admit we cannot attaine to the cleareneſſe of the Sunne or Moone, yet we muſt deſire the brightnes of a ſtarre how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t inferior to them, let vs ſeeke at the leaſt for ſome light by our good deeds, let vs la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to be ſound, worthy, to inlarge ſomewhat the ſhining of heauen. If we cannot be gold, if we cannot be precious ſtones, yet let vs be in ſtead of ſiluer, onely let vs now be turned into that matter, which fire may conſume, that we be not found to be wood, hay, or ſtubble, let vs be euen the laſt in goodnes, not the firſt in euill.<note n="*" place="margin">By of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding a little, there will ariſe a great heape as wittily ſaid Heſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odus.
<q>
                           <l>
                              <gap reason="foreign">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap>,</l>
                           <l>
                              <gap reason="foreign">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap>.</l>
                        </q> Small good workes conioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with faith and repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance go not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</note> And as worldly riches increaſe, when euery ſmall gaine is regarded: ſo it fareth in heauenly riches, in increaſing the which no little good deede muſt be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>temned.
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:22457:70"/> Surely it is an abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity, (ſeeing our Iudge doth not deny a reward for<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat</hi> 10</note> a cup of cold water) for vs to ſay, that vnleſſe wee doe great things, it wil be nothing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaileable. Yea this more I ad, that he that deſpiſeth not ſmall and little things, will by little and little come to great things and<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Eccl.</hi> 19.1</note> he that contemneth ſmall things, (which concordeth with the Scripture) ſhall fall by little and little. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I thinke for this cauſe, our Lord and Sauiour did ordaine for ſmall things great rewardes. For what is leſſe, than to viſit the ſicke? And yet for this ſmall worke, hee hath laid vp a great reward. And againe, what is ſo eaſie, as to giue the hungry bread, the thirſtie drinke, the naked raiment, and to ſeeke out him that is ſhut vp in priſon? Yet theſe things that be ſo little and ſmall, he reckneth ſo great as that he accounteth them
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:22457:71"/> miniſtred not to man, but to himſelfe, and for them hath promiſed the celeſtiall king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
                  <p>Wherefore (moſt deerely belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued) enter, enter the waye to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall life, and put on againe<note n="*" place="margin">My yoke is light, &amp; my bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den light, This bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den is not the weight of him that is loden, but the winges of him that flieth For birds haue bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens of their fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, which on earth they beare, &amp; of them they are borne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine.</note> the yoake of Chriſt which is eaſie, and his burden which is light, recouer the vertues of thy mind, make thine end ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to thy beginning, let not the treaſure of ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall graces, gotten by ſuch labour, decay, and they will verely periſh, if thou perſiſt in euils, &amp; exaſperate the wrath of God againſt thy deedes. But before thou looſe much of thy treaſure, and before thy manured field be ſurrounded with hurtfull deluges, if thou exclude the entrance, and ſtop the ouerflowing of ſinne, thou maiſt bring it againe to his priſtine fertility, and by huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banding make it very battle.</p>
                  <p>Ariſe therefore, ariſe and ſhake off the duſt from thee,
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:22457:71"/> ariſe from the earth, and ſtraightway (beleeue mee) thine enemy will be affraid. For he threw thee downe, as though thou ſhouldeſt neuer riſe vp, but if he ſhall ſee thee to riſe from the earth, and lift thine eyes towards the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens, incontinent thy bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes will out-countenance him,<note n="*" place="margin">Reſiſt the deuil, and he will flie ftom you. <hi>Jam.</hi> 4.7 If one flie the deuill he is a Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: if one reſiſt, he hath (for he is Bel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>zebub, that is, a God of flies) no more power than a weak flie: according to the old verſe.
<q>
                           <l>Hoſtis non laedit, niſi cum tentàtus obedit,</l>
                           <l>Eſt leo ſi cedis, ſi ſtas quafi muſca recedit.</l>
                        </q>
                     </note> and the more ready thou art, the more fearefull he will be, and the more thou preſumeſt, the more fraile and infirme thou makeſt him. Thinke alſo on this, that the more hardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe God ſhall indue thee withall, the more he will wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken both his boldneſſe and might.</p>
                  <p>If ſo be thou haue affiance in my wordes, me thinketh I ſee towards thee the mercy and aide of God, but thine
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:22457:72"/> aduerſary to be affrighted by reaſon of ſhame and confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Me thinketh I perceiue now in my mind, that with all gratefulnes and fauour euery vertue allureth thee to her, hold on then earneſtly, labour chearefully, runne forward willingly. Thou ſhalt find no want of me in that I can, but I will ſtill reaſon with thee in ſpeech, I will continually ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort and ſtir thee vp, both pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent with liuely voice, and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent with letters. Albeit I perſwade my ſelfe, if thou glad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly read this I haue now writ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten, there will bee no cauſe, why thou ſhouldeſt ſeeke for farther medicines.</p>
                  <closer>Deo ſoli ſapienti, laus &amp; gloria.</closer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb n="133" facs="tcp:22457:72"/>
                  <head>TO THE Reader.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked would earneſtlie conſider, the terriblenes of the day of the Lord, it muſt needes bee, that they would either wholy renounce ſinne, or at leaſt, not ſo much bee delighted therewith.
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:22457:73"/> VVhich Chriſoſtome right wel perceiued, for that ſo copiouſly, ſo liuely (as it were with a pencile) he depainteth that day and time. On the other ſide, to pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der equally the rewards that in heauen abide for them, who in this life ſeeke chiefly the ſetting forth of Gods glory, &amp; the benefitting of their neighbour, who bewai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling theyr ſinnes with true and vnfayned re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, by the hand of faith lay hold on Gods promiſes, auay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth not a little, to the
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:22457:73"/> abandoning of ſinne and iniquitie. VVhere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (gentle Reader) in the ſentences follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing I haue vſed this or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that thoſe which appartaine to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond comming of Chriſt, and the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the vngodly are ſet firſt, in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond place thoſe that ſhew the ioyes of the world to come, and in the laſt roome thoſe that teach, that by faith, ſincere repentance, and amendment of our liues, we may inioy that heauenly bliſſe. My pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:22457:74"/> to thee is this, that thou daine to ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cept my labour, which if thou doe, I ſhall bee occaſioned to iudge my trauell well beſtowed, The Lord of his mercy grant, that, ſith wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes neuer more aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, nor men neuer leſſe remembred, the comming of Chriſt, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to iudgement, wee may heartely repent vs of our ſinnes, becauſe the wrath of God hangeth ouer our heads: and that wee may, as good Chriſtians, liue worthy of our vocation, (liuing
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:22457:74"/> ſo as though euery one particularly ſhould ſay, with that holy man S. <hi>Hierome,</hi> as often as I remember that day, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery member of my body quaketh: for whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I eate or drinke, or do any thing elſe, mee thinketh alwaies that dreadful trumpet ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in mine eares, ariſe O ye dead, and come to iudgement, becauſe the laſt houre is at hand. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>As deſirous of thy profit, as of his owne, in the ſchoole of Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> R. Wol.</signed>
                  </closer>
                  <epigraph>
                     <bibl>OENIPODES.</bibl>
                     <q>
                        <hi>Non ciſtae, ſed pectori.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:22457:75"/>
                  <pb n="139" facs="tcp:22457:75"/>
                  <head>Sentences collected out of the fathers workes, which haue ſuch agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with the former Treatiſe, as that they are not vnfit for this place. Of the puniſhments of hell, and of the day of iudgement.</head>
                  <q>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N that terrible ho wex of the death of a wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched ſinner,<note place="margin">Bernard in ſpec. pec,</note> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly there will come euil ſpirits (like roaring lions) to ſnatch a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way their pray. When ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:22457:76"/> ſhal appeare the hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible places of torments, the Chaos and obſcuritie of darkeneſſe, the dread of miſerie and confuſion, the terror of that fearefull manſion, where is the place of weepers, where is the place of groaners, where is the voyce of them that crie wo, wo, wo bee to vs the children of Euah when the miſerable ſoule departing from the body ſhall heare, ſee, and ſeele theſe and ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>blable thinges, yea a thouſand times worſe then may be ſpoken, in what (I pray,) how great, and how wonde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous feare and trembling ſhall ſhee be? what tongue can vtter it, what booke declare it? what will now auaile the boaſting of knowledge, the pompe of the people, the vanitie of
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:22457:76"/> the world, the greedineſſe of earthly dignitie? what ſhall then auaile the appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite of ryot, delitiouſneſſe of meate, exquiſite drinke, curioſitie of garments, niceneſſe of the fleſh, glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tony of the belly, ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of foode, ſurfet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and drunkenneſſe, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious building of houſes, poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of terrene goods, ſcraping together of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bends, hoording of riches? whether can theſe thinges deliuer the wretched ſoule of a man from the mouth of the hydious and horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Lion, that is, from the iawe of the curſed dragon.</q>
                  <q>when that cunning de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuer,<note place="margin">Idem. ibid.</note> that ſonne of iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, that moſt eager enemy of our ſoules, ſhall miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably and dreadfully meet with thy ſoule, how wilt thou be able to abide the
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:22457:77"/> fearefull ſight of his terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble countenance, the intol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable ſtink of his mouth, the brimſtone-like flames of his eyes? How then wilt thou be of force to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide ſo great feare, of ſo horrible a beaſt? Be aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that the feare of his dreadfull preſence, excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth euery kind of tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſed in this world. At which the Prophet qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king betooke himſelfe to prayer, ſaying, heare my prayer O God when I call vpon thee, deliuer my ſoule from the feare of the enemy. He ſaid not from the power of the enemy, but from the feare of the enemy. But alas, my bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, if the ſinfull ſoule bee ſo much, and ſo greatly daunted at the ſight onely of Sathan, how great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:22457:77"/> or how great hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, how great affiction, and how great lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhal ſhe haue through his touching and tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting?</q>
                  <q>when the Lord ſhall be about to iudge the ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull world,<note place="margin">Hierom. ad Heliod.</note> it ſhall make a great noyſe, and one kindred ſhal ſtrike the breaſt to another kindred. The Kinges once moſt puiſſaunt, ſhall quake without a guard, fooliſh Plato with his ſchollers ſhal be brought forth, then Ariſtotles argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts ſhall not be profitable, when that ſonne of the poore wo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>man which exerciſed a craft ſhall come to iudge the endes of the earth.</q>
                  <q>That iudge is neyther preuented with fauour,<note place="margin">Augu. li. <hi>3.</hi> de ſymb.</note> nor mooued with pitty, nor bribed with money,
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:22457:78"/> neyther will he be appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with ſatſfaction, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance. Here let the ſoul deale for it ſelfe while it hath time, as long as there is a place for mercy, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there will be a place of iuſtice.</q>
                  <q>
                     <note place="margin">Greg. hom. <hi>15.</hi>
                     </note>In the laſt day of iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, when the heauens being opened, the Angels miniſtring, the Apoſtles ſitting together, Chriſt ſhall appeare in the ſeate of his maieſtie, all the elect &amp; reprobate ſhal ſee him, that both the iuſt may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce without end of the gift of theyr reward, and the vniuſt euer lament, for the reuengement of theyr plague.</q>
                  <q>
                     <note place="margin">Anſel. de ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militudini bus mundi</note>On the right hand there ſhall be our ſinnes to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe vs, on the left hand in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite deuils, beneath the horrible confuſion of hell,
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:22457:78"/> aboue an angry Iudge, without the worlde fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, within our conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence burning, there ſcarce the iuſt ſhall be ſaued. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacke wretched ſinner, whither wilt thou flee? It is impoſſible to be hidden, intollerable to appeare.</q>
                  <q>The ioy of the time pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent muſt be ſo vſed,<note place="margin">Greg hom. <hi>32.</hi>
                     </note> that the remembrance of the bitternes of the iudgment to come, may neuer depart from vs.</q>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of the ioyes of heauen.</head>
                     <q>SO great is the beautie of righteouſnes,<note place="margin">Aug. lib. de morb.</note> ſo great is the ſweetneſſe of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting light, that is, of the immutable wiſdome, that although we might not tarrie in it more then one day, for this alone, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable yeares of this
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:22457:79"/> life repleniſhed with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights and aboundance of temporal goods, were not without cauſe and reaſon to be contemned.</q>
                     <q>
                        <note place="margin">Jdem. li, <hi>3.</hi> de. ſymb.</note>Wee can eaſilier tell what there is not in that eternall life, then what there is. There is not death, there is not mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, there is not weari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, there is not weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, there is not hunger, there is no thirſt, no par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching heat, no corruption, no lacke, no ſorrowe, no ſadneſſe.</q>
                     <q>Make haſte thither, where you may liue for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer.<note place="margin">Ide. devtil. agen. poen.</note> For if you ſo loue this miſerable and tranſitorie life, wherein you liue with ſuch labour, and wherein by running, trauelling, ſweating, breathing, thou ſcarce get things neceſſary for the body: how much
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:22457:79"/> more ought you to loue the life euerlaſting, where you ſhall ſuſtaine no la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, where alwaies is great quietnes, great fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitie, happy libertie, hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py bleſſedneſſe, where ſhal be fulfilled that the Lorde ſpake in the Goſpell, Men ſhall be like the Angels. And that, the iuſt ſhall ſhine, &amp;c.</q>
                     <q>Temporall life compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with eternall life,<note place="margin">Greg. in homil.</note> is rather to be called death then life. For the daily fainting of corruption, what is it els, but a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine long continuance of death? But what tongue can tell, or what vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding conceiue, how great theſe ioyes are of that ſupernall Cittie, to be in the aſſembly of Angels, with the moſt bleſſed ſoules to ſtand by the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:22457:80"/> of the Creator, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde in preſence the face of God, to ſee that immea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurable light, to feele no pangs of death, to enioy the gift of euer-enduring incorruption.</q>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Againſt deſpaire.</head>
                     <q>THe theefe acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged,<note place="margin">Aug. in lib. de ſymb.</note> Peter denied. In Peter there is ſhewed, that no iuſt man ought to preſume of himſelfe: in the theefe, that no wicked man being conuerted, ſhould deſpaire. Therefore let the good feare, leaſt he periſh through pride, and let not the wicked deſpair throgh much naughtines.</q>
                     <q>
                        <note place="margin">Idem de vtil. agen. poen.</note>Let none deſpaire as Iudas the traitor: not ſo much the haynous wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe which he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, was the cauſe of
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:22457:80"/> his eternall deſtruction, as the deſpaire of forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</q>
                     <q>Let none diſtruſt,<note place="margin">Amb. ſup. Luc. lib. <hi>2.</hi>
                        </note> let none in the priuitie of his olde ſinnes deſpaire of the rewardes of God. God knoweth how to change his determination, if thou know how to amend thy fault.</q>
                     <q>Let no man deſpaire of pardon,<note place="margin">Iſido. de ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. bon. lib. <hi>2.</hi>
                        </note> although about the end of his life, he bee turned to repentance. God iudgeth euerie one accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his end, not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his life paſt.</q>
                     <q>To commit ſome foule offence is the death of the ſoule: but to deſpaire,<note place="margin">Idem. ibid.</note> is to deſcend into hell.</q>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of Repentance.</head>
                     <q>IF I proffer thee golde,<note place="margin">Amb. in ſer de eleem. &amp; ieiun.</note> thou ſayeſt not, I will
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:22457:81"/> come to morrow, but at the inſtant thou requireſt it, none prolongeth, none maketh excuſe: the redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of our ſoule is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, and none maketh haſt. Conuerſion is neuer too late, the theefe went from the Croſſe to Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe.</q>
                     <q>
                        <note place="margin">Hier. in ep. ad Laetam Greg. hom. <hi>34.</hi> ſup. eua</note>There is greater ioy in heauen of a ſinner conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, then of a righteous man that ſtandeth: for a captaine alſo in warre lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth that ſouldier more, who being returned from flight hath valiantly ſlaine his foe, then him, that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer fled, and hath neuer done any manly act. So the huſbandman loueth more that ground, which after thornes yeldeth forth plentifull corne: then that which neuer had thornes, and neuer bare a fertile
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:22457:81"/> graine.</q>
                     <q>In nothing to ſinne is only the property of God,<note place="margin">Amb. ep. <hi>3</hi> ad Simpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cianum.</note> it is the propertie of a wiſe man, both to correct his fault, and to repent for his ſinne.</q>
                     <q>with God not ſo much the meaſure of time,<note place="margin">Hierom. in quod ſerm</note> as the meaſure of griefe preuai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, not ſo much the abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nencie of meates, as the mortificatton of vices.</q>
                     <q>Repentance is the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine of our wound,<note place="margin">Iſid. li. <hi>3.</hi> de ſum. bon.</note> the hope of ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, by which ſinners are ſalued, by which God is prouoked to mercy. The which is not weighed by time, but by deepeneſſe of lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and teares.</q>
                     <q>O repentance, what new thing ſhall I ſpeake of thee?<note place="margin">Cyprian. de laud. paen.</note> Thou looſeſt all thinges which are boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, thou openeſt al thinges
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:22457:82" rendition="simple:additions"/> which are ſhut, thou miti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gateſt all aduerſitie, thou healeſt that is bruiſed, thou illumineſt that is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded, thou incourageſt all that is out of hope,</q>
                     <q>Be not negligent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Lord forbeareth you when you ſinne,<note place="margin">Aug. in lib. de vti. poen.</note> for how much the longer hee waiteth that ye amend, ſo much the more grieuouſly will hee puniſh if you bee negligent,</q>
                     <q>
                        <note place="margin">Idem de <hi>10</hi> chordis</note>Better is a little bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in the cheekes, then a perpetuall torment in the bowels.</q>
                     <q>
                        <note place="margin">Id. de poen.</note>Althogh the theefe was pardoned in his latter end of all his ſins, yet he gaue not an example to them that are baptized to ſinne, and perſeuere in euill. For then he was firſt baptized with the baptiſme of the ſpirit, in that then firſt hee
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:22457:82"/> profeſſed Chriſt.</q>
                     <q>The ſweeteneſſe of the apple recompenceth the ſowreneſſe of the roote,<note place="margin">Hier. ſuper Mat.</note> the dangers of the ſea for hope of gaine delight vs, the hope of health aſſwageth the griefe of phiſicke. Hee that deſireth the kirnell, breaketh the nut, and hee that will be partaker of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting goodneſſe, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penteth.</q>
                     <q>It is no great matter to fall in wreſtling, but to lie when one is caſt downe.<note place="margin">Chryſ. in ep ad Heliod. Monach.</note> It is not deadly to bee wounded in battle, but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the wound is inflicted, through deſpaire to be cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, to deny a plaiſter to the bile. And oftentimes we ſee wreſtlers crowned, after often ſlides, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny downe-caſts. VVe ſee alſo a ſouldier after many flights to bee a ſtout man,
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:22457:83"/> and to ouercome him that diſcomfited him.</q>
                     <q>Behold the kingdome of God is to be ſolde:<note place="margin">Aug. de ſpir &amp; anima</note> buy it if thou wilt. Neither think of ſome great thing for the greatneſſe of the price, it is worth ſo much as thou haſt, ſeeke not what thou haſt, but what manner of body thou art. This thing is worth ſo much as thou art, giue thy ſelfe and thou ſhalt haue it. But I am euill, thou wilt ſay, and happily it will not receiue me, by gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing thy ſelfe vnto it thou ſhalt be good.</q>
                     <q>
                        <note place="margin">Idem in ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liloquijs.</note>That repentance is in vaine, which afterward a fault polluteth, lamentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons profit nothing, if ſins be doubled. It auaileth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to craue pardon of euils, and anew to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit euils.</q>
                     <q>
                        <pb n="155" facs="tcp:22457:83"/>Hee that knocketh his breaſt,<note place="margin">Idem in quoda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. ſer.</note> and correcteth not himſelfe, ſtrengtheneth his ſinnes, and doth not take them away.</q>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>NAZIANZENVS.</bibl>
                        <lg>
                           <l>
                              <gap reason="foreign">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap>,</l>
                           <l>
                              <gap reason="foreign">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap>.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </q>
                     <q>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Sicubi chalcógraphus titubârit lector amice,</l>
                           <l>Da veniam lapſo, ſic petis ipſe tibi.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </q>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:22457:84"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22457:84"/>
                  <p>AN EPISTLE <hi>OF</hi> COMFORT, From one Friend to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, wherein the Anabaptiſts error of Deſperation is briefly confuted, and the Sinne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Holy Ghoſt plainly declared.</p>
                  <p>Whereunto is added certaine <hi>effectuall Prayers.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>LONDON Printed for <hi>Iohn Helme.</hi> 1609.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="letter">
                  <pb facs="tcp:22457:85"/>
                  <pb n="159" facs="tcp:22457:85"/>
                  <head>An Epiſtle of comfort from one friend to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, wherein the Anabaptiſts error of deſperation is brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly confuted, and the ſinne againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy Ghoſt plainely decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</head>
                  <head type="sub">VVhereunto is added certaine effectuall Prayers</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>yr, whereas it pleaſed you to require mee to write vnto you my mind, concerning the true ſenſe and meaning of this place of Saint Paule in his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle to the Hebrewes.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.</note> It can not be that they which were once lightned, and haue taſted of the he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gift, and were become partakers of the holy Ghoſt, and hauing taſted
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:22457:86"/> of the good word of God, and of the power of the world to come, if they fall away (and as concerning themſelues, crucifie the ſonne of God afreſh, and make a mocke of him) that they ſhould be renued a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine by repentance.</p>
                  <p>Syr, Many in time paſt, and at this preſent day, miſtaking this text and not truely vnderſtanding it,<note place="margin">The error of the No<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uatians &amp; now of the Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts.</note> both haue bene and are encombred with the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uations error, which is, that after man by baptiſme and the holy ghoſt is rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerated, and hath taſted of the grace of God, and hath embraced Chriſt and his holy word, if he fall to ſin againe, he is without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy of ſaluation.</p>
                  <p>Vndoubtedly this is a very damnable error, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to bring all them
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:22457:86"/> that are infected therewith to deſperation. But albeit they ground this their er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror vpon this afore alledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed text of Saint Paule, &amp; certaine other texts: yet they miſſe the cuſhion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they take this ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture too ſtraightly, not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring it to many other places of ſcripture, which ſhew: that whenſoeuer &amp; how often ſoeuer a ſinner repenteth him truly of his ſinnes, and committeth himſelfe with a ſure faith vnto the mercy of God through Chriſt, God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueth him again to grace and ſaluation.</p>
                  <p>Doubtleſſe no prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie in the ſcripture hath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny priuate interpretation,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Petri.</hi> 1.</note> but muſt needes be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded according to the generall articles of the Chriſtian faith and agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:22457:87"/> to other texts of holy ſcripture, and ſo muſt this text be alſo.</p>
                  <p>Now truth it is: that there is almoſt innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble texts in holy ſcripture, that moſt plainely doe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare: that whenſoeuer a true repentant ſinner by vnfayned faith returneth vnto God, &amp; aſketh mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy for Chriſts ſake, he ſhal vndoubtedly haue it. And albeit the holy ſcripture is full of ſuch places, yet here by Gods grace, I will ſhew and rehearſe to you ſome of them, to giue you occaſion to marke them &amp; ſuch like places as you ſhall find almoſt in euery leafe of the Bible.</p>
                  <p>A iuſt man falleth ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen times,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pro,</hi> 2-4</note> and riſeth vpp againe. Marke the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſaith: he riſeth vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine.</p>
                  <pb n="163" facs="tcp:22457:87"/>
                  <p>The wickedneſſe of the wicked ſhal not hurt him,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ezech.</hi> 33.</note> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſoeuer he conuerteth. Note that it ſaith: when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer he conuerteth.</p>
                  <p>Let the vngodly man forſake his owne way,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eſa.</hi> 55.</note> and the vnrighteous his own imaginations and turne againe vnto the Lord, ſo ſhall hee be mercifull vnto him:</p>
                  <p>Thou diſobedient Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell turne againe (ſayth the Lorde) and I will not let my wrath fall vpon you.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iere.</hi> 3.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thus ſaith the Lorde:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Jere.</hi> 8.</note> doe men fall ſo, that they riſe not vp againe? Or if Iſraell doe repent, wil not God turn againe to them?<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Zacha.</hi> 1.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Turne you vnto mee (ſaith the Lord God of hoaſtes) and I will turne me vnto you.</p>
                  <p>Remember from whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Apoc.</hi> 2.</note>
                     <pb n="164" facs="tcp:22457:88" rendition="simple:additions"/> thou art fallen, and do the firſt workee.</p>
                  <p>Marke in the Goſpell of Luke the example of the vnthrifty ſonne.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luc.</hi> 15.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Alſo Chriſt ſaid vnto Peter: Peter I haue pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for thee,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luc.</hi> 22.</note> that thy faith fayle not, and when thou art conuerted, ſtrength thy brethren.</p>
                  <p>Marke, he ſaith: when thou art conuerted. Lo, if you weigh theſe places of ſcripture afore alledged, and almoſt innumerable mo of the ſame ſort, you ſhall perceiue euidently, that though a chriſtian haue ſinned neuer ſo oft (as who doth not daily of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend God) yet whenſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer he returneth vnto God by true repentance (which conſiſteth of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trition and a ſure faith in Chriſt Ieſus) he is
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:22457:88"/> aſſured by the word of God to recouer and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue againe the grace, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour and mercy of God, which through his diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience he had worthely loſt, and immediatly to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyfull, abſolute, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect remiſſion and forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of all his ſinns throgh Ieſus Chriſt, in whom he repoſeth all his faith, truſt, and confidence of ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The Goſpell aſſureth him no leſſe ſaying:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iohn.</hi> 3.</note> So God loued the world, that he gaue his onely begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſonne, that whoſoeuer beleeueth in him ſhould not periſh, but haue euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life.</p>
                  <p>Moreouer, if you marke well the examples of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men, which are regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred in holy ſcripture, you ſhall playnely perceiue, that albeit they were high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:22457:89"/> in Gods fauour, yet for all that, many of them had great fals, and committed very heynous offences, but they did riſe vp againe returning to Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy by true repentance and faith, and ſo recouered a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine their former grace, which they through their owne folly had loſt.</p>
                  <p>Aaron was ſo much fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured of God,<note place="margin">Aaron.</note> that by Gods calling he was made the high biſhop and curate ouer his people.</p>
                  <p>And yet at the light re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of the Iſraelites, hee let them make and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the golden Calfe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to his conſcience, by reaſon whereof, both hee and they committed that moſt deteſtable ſinne of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrie, and yet he by true repentaunce and faith re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning to grace was ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued.</p>
                  <pb n="167" facs="tcp:22457:89"/>
                  <p>Dauid<note place="margin">Dauid,</note> Gods deare dar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ling, after he had y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God, and had much taſted of his grace, being endued aboundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with the holy Ghoſt and gratious gifts from aboue, fell both into the ſin of adulterie and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And yet by true and vnfeyned repentaunce, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning to Gods mercy, was accepted and receiued againe into Gods fauour.</p>
                  <p>Manaſſes<note place="margin">Manaſſes,</note> alſo contrary vnto his conſcience fell willingly to Idolatry, but yet he roſe againe by true repentance and faith, and recouered again the grace of God.</p>
                  <p>So likewiſe that wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed man of the Citie of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthus whome Saint Paul ſtraightly charged the Corinthians to exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate,<note place="margin">The ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Cor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>inthian. 1 Cor. 5.</note> and exclude out
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:22457:90"/> of the holy congregation of Chriſtian men, and that they ſhould neyther eate nor drinke with him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of his open and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominable crime of inceſt and outragious whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: and yet when he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared himſelfe to be truely repentaunt for his great and infamous ſin,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.</note> Saint Paul admoniſhed them with all gentleneſſe and chriſtian charity to receiue him againe into the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation as a chriſtian brother, and ſo to eſteeme him and take him.</p>
                  <p>VVhat ſhall I ſay of Peter<note place="margin">Peter.</note> Chriſts Apoſtle? had not he a ſure know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Chriſt, confeſſing him openly before all the Apoſtles to be very Chriſt the ſonn of the liuing God? was not hee euen then en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with the holy ghoſt
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:22457:90"/> &amp; grace from aboue,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.</note> vnto whome Ieſus Chriſt ſaid: Bleſſed art thou Simon the ſonn of Ionas, for fleſh and bloud hath not opened that vnto thee, but my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther which is in heauen: And yet after all this hee had ſuch a fall, that contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to his owne conſcience, willingly without any co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſion, threates, or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment: he did moſt cowardly and ſhameful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly forſake and deny Chriſt not without blaſphemy, ſwearing that he neuer knew him, curſing and committing himſelfe to the deuill if euer he had to doe with him.</p>
                  <p>VVhat would the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatian and Anabaptiſt ſay vnto this? was it not a fal? could there be any greater ſinne then this? was it not done of knowledge? was
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:22457:91"/> it not done willingly? was it not againſt his owne conſcience? Yes doubtles, it was no leſſe but againſt his owne conſcience. But yet thankes be vnto Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, it was not the ſinne of blaſphemy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the holy ghoſt, ney<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther the ſinne vnto death, the which Saint Iohn ſpeaketh of, for he continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not therein vnto his end,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Iohn.</hi> 5.</note> but immediatly hee went forth of the biſhop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> houſe and wept bitterly, very much lamenting his heynous offence, and by faith he returned againe vnto Chriſt, knowing his mercy to be infinite and without meaſure,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.</note> and ſo he was accepted vnto grace againe, and Chriſt appeared vnto him (to his great comfort) after he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſe againe from death to
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:22457:91"/> life, and afterwards ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding downe his holy ſpirit indued him with wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full gifts of grace from a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>boue. And then <hi>Peter</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a ſtrong champion, ſetting forth Chriſt to be the onely Sauiour of the whole world, preaching and openly confeſſing him before all men, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out any feare either of the Scribes Phariſes or Magiſtrates.</p>
                  <p>Now good ſir, lay this example of Saint <hi>Peter</hi> to this text of Saint <hi>Paule</hi> to the Hebrewes. It cannot be that they which were once lightned. &amp;c. If they fall away, &amp;c. that they ſhould be renued againe by repentance.</p>
                  <p>If a man would apply the aforeſaid example of <hi>S. Peter</hi> vnto this text of Saint <hi>Paule,</hi> hee would thinke that <hi>Peter</hi> ſhould
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:22457:92"/> vtterly haue bene caſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from Gods fauour mercy and grace. For firſt <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> it can not be denyed, but that he was once lightned, that is: endued with the true knowledge of Chriſt to be the onely Meſſias &amp; Sauiour of the world. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, he had alſo caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of the heauenly gift, which wes a true faith in Chriſt Ieſus, openly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing the ſame before all the Apoſtles, being fully perſwaded in his owne <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> conſcience what Chriſt was. Thirdly, that Peter was become partaker of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> holy Ghoſt, &amp; had taſted of the good word of God, it appeareth euidently by Chriſtes ſentence, ſaying Bleſſed art thou Simon, for fleſh and bloud (that is man) ſhewed thee not that but my Father which is
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:22457:92"/> in heauen. VVhich was, by the inſpiration of his holy ſpirit.</p>
                  <p>Finally, <hi>Peter</hi> had a taſt of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> the world to come. For he did ſee in the mountaine the tranſfiguration of Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat,</hi> 17.</note> and ſo did Iames the more, and Iohn the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangeliſt alſo. VVhere, in the preſence of them all Chriſt was tranſfigured and ſhewed himſelfe vnto them in the forme of a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified body, ſo that his face did ſhine as the Sun, and his cloathes appeared as white as the light, there appeared alſo among the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Moſes and Elias. And e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen there the cleare voyce of God the father of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, was plainely hearde among them out of the cloud, ſaying vpon Chriſt, this is my dearly beloued ſonne, in whom I delight, heare him</p>
                  <pb n="174" facs="tcp:22457:93"/>
                  <p>Loe, all this and much more <hi>Peter</hi> both heard and ſaw, being almoſt continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in Chriſts company, eating and drinking with him, hearing dayly his heauenly Doctrine, prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching and teaching, ſeeing euery where (as occaſion ſerued) his great and wonderful myracles. And yet for all this, what a great fall <hi>Peter</hi> had, it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth plainely by his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall of Chriſt his louing maſter and Sauiour, and the circumſtances thereof, which I touched before. But yet to make <hi>Peters</hi> fall more horrible, Chriſt ſaid vnto him, and vnto all other his Apoſtles, when he ſent them forth to preach the Goſpell of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, He that denyeth me before men, I ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny him alſo before my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Alas good <hi>Peter,</hi>
                     <pb n="175" facs="tcp:22457:93"/> what caſe ſtandedſt thou in now? How doth this ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Chriſt now touch thee? Remembring this ſaying of Chriſt, art thou not at thy wies end? Is it not moſt certaine &amp; true, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou haſt too horribly fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len after that thou haddeſt taſted of al theſe gracious gifts before reherſed? Haſt thou not contrary to thine own co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience moſt ſham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully denyed thy maſter &amp; Sauiour before men? Ah good ſoule what ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of thee? how wilt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> anſwere for thy ſelfe? For it ſeemeth here plainely, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> both <hi>S. Paule</hi> in the afore a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged place to the Heb. &amp; alſo Chriſt himſelfe in the ſcripture afore rehearſed, haue giuen ſentence of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation againſt thee. VVherefore, the Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts grounding vpon theſe ſcriptures wil plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ely
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:22457:94"/> pronounce thee to be a reprobate, and that thou art diſpatched and vtterly caſt away from all hope of ſaluation. But here let vs not too lightly paſſe ouer, but earneſtly and deeply conſider, what may be ſaid in this matter on <hi>Peters</hi> behalfe. And firſt it may be rightly anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that that place of S. <hi>Paule</hi> vnto the Hebrews,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.</note> maketh nothing againſt S. <hi>Peter,</hi> neither yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt any Chriſtian man how grieuouſly or how often ſoeuer he hath ſinned ſo that he hath not vtterly forſaken Chriſt and fallen cleane away from him.</p>
                  <p>For S. <hi>Paule</hi> ſaith: It cannot be that they which were once lightned. &amp;c. If they fall away, &amp;c. that they ſhould be renued by repentance.</p>
                  <pb n="177" facs="tcp:22457:94"/>
                  <p>Marke here diligently,<note place="margin">It is not all one thing to fall, and to fall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way,</note> that S. <hi>Paule</hi> ſaith, if they fall away. He ſaith not if they fall: but if they fall away, for it is not all one thing to fall, and to fall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. For <hi>Peter</hi> did fal, but did not fall away from Chriſt, but returned vnto him againe. And old pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbe<note place="margin">A pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbe,</note> it is: a man runneth very farre, that neuer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th againe. All wee Chriſtians doe daily fall, for we daily breake Gods commandements, but yet we doe not fall away from Chriſt, neither refuſe wee him to be our Sauiour, but acknowledging our manifold ſinnes and offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, we daily turne vnto him againe, by true repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, faith and amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of life, nothing doubting of his great and vnmeaſurable mercy to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards vs.</p>
                  <pb n="178" facs="tcp:22457:95"/>
                  <p>They fall away from Chriſt that vtterly forſake him and refuſe him,<note place="margin">Who fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth away fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> chriſt.</note> to be their Sauiour, and neuer returne vnto him againe to obtaine his mercy, but are become plaine apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaes, vtterly forſaking the chriſtian faith, making but a mocke of Chriſt, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuering in their obſtinate apoſtacy and vnbeleefe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to their liues end. As did <hi>Iudas</hi> the traitor,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.</note> 
                     <hi>Iulia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Apoſtata, Simon</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus, <hi>Porphyrius, Hymeneus</hi> and <hi>Alexander</hi> the Coper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmith.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. A good &amp; gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall rule to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note>Secondarily, as touching that ſaying and threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of Chriſt, ſaying: He that denyeth mee before men, I ſhall deny him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my father, &amp;c. It is to be conſidered, that all the terrible threatnings that are in the holy Scripture
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:22457:95"/> threatned againſt great ſinners are threatned con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditionally, that is to ſay: if the ſinners do not truely repent and returne vnto God by faith and amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of life, this plague or puniſhment or that, ſhal light vpon them. But if they at the preaching, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding or hearing of Gods holy word, do repente and returne vnto God, by faith and godly life, then that plague threatned ſhal not once touch them. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample be the Niniuites vpon whom <hi>Ionas</hi> Gods miniſter and preacher (or rather God by him) pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced this terrible iudg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment ſaying,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ion.</hi> 3.</note> there are yet forty dayes, and then ſhall <hi>Niniue,</hi> bee ouerthrowne. But there as the ſcripture ſaith, the people of <hi>Niniue</hi> beleeued God &amp; earneſtly
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:22457:96"/> repented them of their great ſinnes, and ſo was the ſentence of God retrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and the Cittie ſaued and not ouerthrowne. So likewiſe this terrible ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Chriſt, he that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyeth mee before men, I ſhall deny him before my Father, muſt needes haue this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dition ioyned with it, if he doth not repent, neyther returne againe,<note place="margin">A condit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> but <hi>Peter</hi> did both repent, and returne againe vnto Chriſt. For albeit his faith was weake and faint (as was the faith of all the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles) yet it was not vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly extinct:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.</note> for Chriſt had ſaid vnto him before, <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> I haue prayed for thee that thy faith faile not.</p>
                  <p>And in any wiſe take heede, and note this well, Chriſt ſaide not, hee that denyeth mee, I ſhall deny
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:22457:96"/> him, though he repent and returne, but remember well that Chriſt ſaid,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.</note> I came not to call the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, but ſinners vnto repentaunce. <hi>Peter</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore repented, and retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto Chriſt againe, and ſo was receiued vnto grace, and was ſaued.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſtion </seg>
                     </label> VVherefore good Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, in this hard text of Saint <hi>Paule</hi> vnto the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes, way wel this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, (if they fall away) for they onely fall away, which commit that moſt horrible crime, which is called in the holy ſcripture the ſinne vnto death, blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy againſt the ſpirit, and the ſinne againſt the holy Ghoſt, which neuer ſhall be forgiuen, neyther in this world, neyther in the world to come.</p>
                  <p>But here it might bee
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:22457:97"/> demaunded what the ſinne againſt the holy Ghoſt is, and wherein it differeth from all other greeuous ſinnes. <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere. </seg>
                     </label> VVhereunto I anſwere, that there is dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference in ſinnes, it may clearely be gathered of Chriſtes wordes ſaying,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.</note> I ſay vnto you, all ſinne and blaſphemy ſhall bee forgiuen vnto men, but the blaſphemy againſt the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit ſhall not be forgiuen vnto men.</p>
                  <p>Loe, here is the matter plainely opened by our Sauiour Chriſt what kind of ſinnes ſhal be forgiuen, and what neuer forgiuen, blaſphemy againſt the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit ſhall neuer be forgiuen, all other ſinne and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy ſhall be forgiuen. And Chriſt in ſaying all ſinne ſhall be forgiuen, compriſeth both originall
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:22457:97"/> ſinne,<note place="margin">Three ſorts of ſinnes, Sinne Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſpirit.</note> and alſo actuall ſinne: moreouer Chriſt ſpeaketh here of three ſorts of ſinns, the firſt he calleth ſinne, the ſecond blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and the third blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> againſt the ſpirit: which the ſcripture alſo calleth the ſinne vnto death, and the ſinne againſt the holy ghoſt. Theſe three kindes of ſinnes, and the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of euery of them, I intend by Gods helpe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerally to declare vnto you ſo ſhortlie as I can, and ſo for this time tom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit you vnto God, And firſt conſider well what ſinne is.</p>
                  <p>Sinne<note place="margin">Sinne.</note> is euery wilfull diſobedience, act, or deede, that is done contrary vnto the Law and commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements of God, without murmur, grudge, or euill ſpeaking: eyther againſt
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:22457:98"/> the Law, commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or God himſelfe, which is the maker and giuer of the Lawe.</p>
                  <p>As is Idolatry, ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, periury, ſwearing vnaduiſedly, breaking of the holy day, diſhonou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring father and mother, murther, malice hatred, enuie, wrath, ſtrife, trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, ſedition, ſlaunder, whordome, theft, and ſuch like.</p>
                  <p>All theſe and ſuch other are called, and are indeede ſinne, ſo long as the doo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of them doe neyther murmur, repine, grudge nor ſpeake euill againſt God or his holy lawe, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther allowe in their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience the thing and euill that they doe, but rather doe vtterly diſalowe, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demne in their own conſcience thoſe their
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:22457:98"/> owne damnable acts as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil and deteſtable.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond kinde of ſinne is blaſphemy, marke it well, and conſider howe it differeth firſt from ſinne, and then from the ſinne againſt the holy ghoſt.</p>
                  <p>Blaſphemy<note place="margin">Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my.</note> is more heynous then is ſinne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, for all blaſphemy is ſinne, but all ſinne is not blaſphemy, for truth it is that blaſphemy compri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth in it ſelfe both ſinne, &amp; alſo a murmure, grudg, reuiling, euill ſpeaking, ſlaunder, and reproach of God and godlineſſe, but it is alway couple<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> with ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noraunce and vnbeleefe, and proceedeth not of ſuch obſtinate malice as conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nueth to the end of the life, as doth the ſinne againſt the holy Ghoſt. In this ſinne of blaſphemy, Saint
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:22457:99"/> Paule offended before his conuerſion vnto the faith of Chriſt Ieſu. For thus he ſpeakkth of himſelfe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I was a blaſphemer,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2</note> and a perſecutor, and a tyraunt, but I obtayned mercy, becauſe I did it ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norantly in vnbeliefe. Lo, here it is plaine and eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that this blaſphemy thogh it be a great offence, yet it is remiſſible, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueable, and is not exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from grace and mercy, becauſe it proceedeth of ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance and not of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, nor of obſtinate ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, that doth endure to the liues end, neyther is it the ſinne vnto death, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we may lawfully pray for ſuch blaſphemers, As Saint Iohn ſaith,<note place="margin">2, <hi>Iohn.</hi> 5</note> if any man ſee his brother ſinne a ſinne not vnto death, let him aſke, and he ſhal giue him life.</p>
                  <pb n="187" facs="tcp:22457:99"/>
                  <p>In this ſimple blſphemy (for ſo wee may call it) ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the Iewes offended, takinge Chriſt to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing leſſe then the ſonne of <hi>Dauid,</hi> or Meſſias, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his parents were ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry poore, and himſelfe ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to be but a poore carpenters ſonne, which bare but a ſimple port in the world, yea and ſome of them that crucified Chriſt, were ouerwhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in this ſimple blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy, and therefore Chriſt prayed for them, ſaying, father forgiue them for they know not what they doe.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luc.</hi> 23.</note> So <hi>Peter</hi> in his ſermon excuſed the crucifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of Chriſt ſaying, now deare breethren I knowe that you haue done it through ignorance &amp;c.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Act</hi> 3.</note> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent you therefore and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, that your ſinnes
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:22457:100"/> may be done away.</p>
                  <p>So did Saint <hi>Steuen</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo pray for his perſecutors whome before hee called ſtifnecked,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Act</hi> 7.</note> aduerſaries of the holy ghoſt, traitors and murtherers of Chriſt, doubtleſſe he would not haue prayed for them ſo earneſtly, vnleſſe their ſinnes had bene forgiuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and therefore their ſin and offence was no more but ſimple blaſphemy.</p>
                  <p>The third kind of ſinn, is blaſphemy againſt the ſpirit.</p>
                  <p>They commit blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my againſt the ſpirit,<note place="margin">Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſpirit.</note> or ſin againſt the holy ghoſt, which willingly, vpon knowledge, and aduiſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, contrary to their owne conſcience doe deny, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ake, impugne, ſlaunder, reuile, and perſecute, the plaine, open, manifeſt, and
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:22457:100"/> knowne truth, ſtifly, mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſly, and obdurately perſeuering, and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing without vnfayned re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentaunce, in that their willfull blindnes and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate malice ſo long as they liue in this world, as did <hi>Pharaoh, Saule, Herod, Iudas</hi> the traytor, <hi>Iulianus Apoſtata, Porphirius, Hime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neus,</hi> and <hi>Alexander</hi> the copper-ſmith with other.</p>
                  <p>But marke this dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently, that wee cannot (as farre as I can per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue) certainely iudge of theſe blaſphemers againſt the ſpirit, before the time of their departure out of this preſent life: becauſe wee cannot certainely knowe, whether at the end of their life they can repent and by faith returne and take holde of the mercy of God or not.</p>
                  <pb n="190" facs="tcp:22457:101"/>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Coniec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine. <hi>Luc.</hi> 23.</note>VVee may coniecture, but we can not (as I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe) certainely define of them. Let vs conſider, that the theefe that hung on the right hand of Chriſt, euen at the laſt houre repented, and with a ſtrong &amp; faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful prayer committed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe wholly vnto the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of Chriſt and was ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. In conſideration whereof, let vs thinke it to be our bounden duty (as the Prophets, Chriſt and his Apoſtles did) to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke, and call backe again open ſinners and blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers to earneſt repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce for their owne ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, and to haue a ſure truſt in the mercy of God, and in the merit of Chriſts paſſion and death, though they be euen at the depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture out of this preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t life. for it is neuer too late ſo
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:22457:101"/> long as life laſteth. Let vs therefore with all feruent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe call vpon them and exhort them in any wiſe with a good courage, and a ſure and vndoubful faith aſke, call and cry for Gods mercy, for his ſweet ſonne our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt his ſake, and vndoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they ſhall haue it. For ſince the beginning of the world hitherto, was there neuer one that in faith aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked mercy heartely, but he had it, through the grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous goodneſſe of our a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid moſt mercifull ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Ieſus Chriſt, vnto whome with the Father and the holy Ghoſt be all honour, laude, and praiſe world without end Amen.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Yours at commaund to his power. T. C. </signed>
                  </closer>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>Giue all the honor laud and praiſe to God onely.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.</note>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <pb facs="tcp:22457:102"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22457:102"/>
                  <head>The prayer of Daniel turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to metre and applyed vnto our time. <hi>Daniel,</hi> IX.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>O Lord thou high and fearefull God</l>
                     <l>By whom all things do moue</l>
                     <l>Thy mercies great are ſure to ſuch</l>
                     <l>As thy precepts doe loue.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>We ſinfull men haue ſore tranſgreſt,</l>
                     <l>Againſt thy lawes deuine</l>
                     <l>Full frowardly we haue fled backe</l>
                     <l>From theſe precepts of thine.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Thy Prophets deare to ſpeake were preſt</l>
                     <l>In ſetting forth thy name.</l>
                     <l>Both rich and poore as bold were bent</l>
                     <l>For to gaineſay the ſame.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>To thee therefore thou Lord of hoaſtes</l>
                     <l>All iuſtice doth belong</l>
                     <l>To poure on vs ſuch ſhame and griefe</l>
                     <l>In this we haue no wrong.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Our ſhame is great and due to all</l>
                     <l>Our flight is but in vaine.</l>
                     <l>To tread ſtrange lands our ſin hath ſought</l>
                     <l>Our ſhame doth ſtill remaine.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:22457:103"/>
                     <l>But though ſuch ſhame a reward iuſt</l>
                     <l>To all in common be</l>
                     <l>Yet mercy Lord and to forgiue</l>
                     <l>Doth ſtill belong to thee.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Indeede (O Lord) as for our ſelues</l>
                     <l>No leſſe confeſſe wee can.</l>
                     <l>But that thy lawes wee ſet at nought</l>
                     <l>Much leſſe haue kept them than.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Thy Prophets ſpake wee would not heare</l>
                     <l>Ne of thee ſtand in awe.</l>
                     <l>Strange plagues from time to time we felt</l>
                     <l>For breaking of thy lawe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The force whereof ſo fiercely bent</l>
                     <l>Was ſuch as hath not bene.</l>
                     <l>For all the plagues in Moſes lawe</l>
                     <l>Fell on this Realme for ſinne.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And yet to thee who made his ſute</l>
                     <l>His path way ſo to guide.</l>
                     <l>That flying vice might learne thy lawe</l>
                     <l>And therein to abide?</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Wwerefore thou ſaweſt all would not helpe</l>
                     <l>And couldſt not hold thine hand.</l>
                     <l>But haſte thy curſe which now doth fall</l>
                     <l>Vpon this ſinfull land.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:22457:103"/>
                     <l>For as thou art a righteous God,</l>
                     <l>Thy workes doe ſoe appeare.</l>
                     <l>Conſuming ſuch as ſcorne doth take</l>
                     <l>Thy louing voyce to heare.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But yet (O Lord) thou broughteſt forth</l>
                     <l>Thy flocke from Egipt land.</l>
                     <l>Whereby thy name was largely ſpread</l>
                     <l>So now ſtretch forth thine hand.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But we haue ſinned more then they</l>
                     <l>Oh Lord yet ſtay thy rod.</l>
                     <l>As for this land was ſometime thine</l>
                     <l>And thou alſo our God.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Our ſinnes and eke our fathers faultes</l>
                     <l>This day to paſſe hath brought.</l>
                     <l>That all which border vs about</l>
                     <l>They ſet vs cleane at nought.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Now then (O Lord) hide not thy face</l>
                     <l>Oh heare thy ſeruaunts cry.</l>
                     <l>Behold thine houſe ſometime full rich</l>
                     <l>How waſt it doth nowe lie.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Thy truth is fled, thy flock faſt bound</l>
                     <l>As ſheepe led to be ſlaine.</l>
                     <l>Thy foes preuaile and proſper much</l>
                     <l>Though miſchiefe they maintaine.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:22457:104"/>
                     <l>And wilt not thou thy foes confound</l>
                     <l>That thus thy workes reproue.</l>
                     <l>At leaſt yet for thy great names ſake</l>
                     <l>Their vile intents remoue.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For why, as for our owne deſerts</l>
                     <l>We can no ſuch thing haue.</l>
                     <l>It is for thy great mercies ſake</l>
                     <l>That we ſuch thinges doe craue.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Forgiue vs Lord, intreated be</l>
                     <l>To heare vs make no ſtay.</l>
                     <l>We beare thy name, it is thy cauſe</l>
                     <l>Oh Lord make no delay.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <pb facs="tcp:22457:104"/>
                  <head>A Prayer againſt Deſpaire.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>O</hi> Eternall God, moſt louing and gratious father in Ieſus Chriſt, who art alwaies prayſed and magnified by thy children, in theyr great deliuerances and preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation from their perils and daungers: but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue themſelues freede from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> power of Satan, death, and hell: from the
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:22457:105"/> which no creature can ſaue and deliuer them, but thou onely O Lorde: And becauſe no chaine of the deuill, or euill temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, is more ſtrong to fetter the body and ſoule of man, then deſpaire: which is a wilfull forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of faith and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in thee O God: it ariſing &amp; ſpringing from fear and doubt: as if thou wert not faithfull in thy promiſes, or able in thy power to preſerue vs: Helpe Lord I beſeech thee, and free and deliuer me thy poore ſeruaunt, from this temptation &amp; thraldome of Satan: and ſoe ſtrengthen (I humbly pray thee) my faith and
<pb facs="tcp:22457:105"/> confidence euer more in thee, that in al my perils, neceſſities, wants, ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes and griefe in this world, I may haue a ſtrong and ſtedfaſt hope in thee, whereby I may ouercome, repell, and keepe backe, the dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and ſubtill ſuggeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Satan, the world and the fleſh: to thy great glory and praiſe, and my eternall and vnſpeakable comfort, through Ieſus Chriſt my onely Lord and Sauiour Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>¶ A Prayer for the Morning.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>O</hi> Lord thou which couereſt the night
<pb facs="tcp:22457:106"/> with darkeneſſe, and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt man therein to take his reſt, and by euery day and night doeſt ſhew thy great glory in the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens, and alſo thy wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and power by go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerning and preſeruing all thy creatures vpon the earth: O Lord I thy poore ſeruaunt and crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, doe moſt humbly thanke thee from the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of my heart, for my ſweete and comfortable reſt this night paſt, and for watching ouer mée by thine eye of prouidence, and kéeping both my bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and ſoule by thy grace from ſinne and death: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeching thée, O Lorde God my father, Sauiour
<pb facs="tcp:22457:106"/> and comforter: to bleſſe, to ſanctifie, direct and preſerue me in this thy new day, and that I may become a newe creature vnto thée O God, in holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and righteouſneſſe, labouring faithfully and painfully in my calling: that ſo my laboures this day may be ſanctified and bleſſed vnto mée and mine: and that I may ſhew forth thy praiſe in al my waies, and declare my loue and charity vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to men in all my works: that after the dayes of this my life and pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage finiſhed and ended here in this world: I may liue with thee for euer in the world to come, throgh
<pb facs="tcp:22457:107"/> Ieſus Chriſt my Lorde and Sauiour, who liueth and reigneth with thée and the holy Ghoſt, euer one God world without end. Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>¶ A Prayer for the Euening.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>O</hi> gratious and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull God, I am moſt bound vnto thy heauenly Maieſty: for my preſeruatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this day, becauſe I and al men, are continually ſubiect vnto all dangers and perils, griefes &amp; ſorrowes, ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and death: yea we lie open (vnles thy grace and might doe defend vs) vnto the temptations &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:22457:107"/> tyranny of the world, the fleſh, &amp; the deuill: which daily ſeek and deſire our hurt and confuſion, both of body &amp; ſoule for euer. Wherefore O gratious and euerliuing God, as thy right hand and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing health, hath bene with mée this day, and thou haſt directed, bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and comforted mee, thy poore ſeruaunt in all my wayes and labours, for the which I moſt hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly thank thée: ſo I moſt earneſtly entreat thy Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty: in thy loue and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy for Chriſt Ieſus ſake, to keepe mée and al mine in ſafety this night, and to couer vs vnder the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of thy winges from
<pb facs="tcp:22457:108"/> all perils and dangers whatſoeuer, and that our ſoules as well as our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies may take their ſwéet and comfortable reſt and ioy in thée: and likewiſe that thou wouldeſt grant that whenſoeuer thou ſhalt knocke at the doore of our hearts to call vs vnto thee O God: we may with the wiſe Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins be watchfull, &amp; haue oyle in our lamps, that we may be receiued into eternall reſt: through Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt thy deare ſonn, and our onely Sauiour: Amen.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22457:108"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
